Paul: Yeah, hello everyone, am I audible? Please let me know in the chat.
Paul: Good morning, everyone, and Happy New Year to everyone.
Paul: Alright guys, so we will continue with our discussion, so let me first of all… Start sharing my screen.
Paul: Alright, to cover how we were planning to cover this book.
Paul: Alrighty, all of you, no, not yet launched.
Paul: It will be launching, probably, I think, this month, probably. Second week or third week.
Paul: There's a pet topic, just wait.
Paul: The coupons, that is provided only once, it's not like that every time we do share.
Paul: So you asked, okay, when we do share, please take the taxes.
Paul: Yes, everything is good now. Thanks for asking.
Paul: Alright guys, so our agenda today, so two things that we'll be discussing. So, continuation of the Lama Intex part. Okay, and finally, we'll be looking into that, chunking part, so very specifically, one library.
Paul: The chonky one we'll be discussing today.
Paul: Okay, so recordings are available. Okay, I actually checked. Okay, so when I went through…
Paul: Recording says, yeah, please have a look, into that one, so…
Paul: Here, if I go as view as customer, okay, the last one is project A3 is written, that will be the llama index. Okay, so don't get confused.
Paul: And on 27th and 28… 27 and 28, there were no classes.
Paul: Okay, so it will be the, like, the second class of llama.
Paul: Yes, 27, 28 more classes, okay?
Paul: Alright, fine, so I think… So, in the last class, a few people requested,
Paul: for AWS models to be used. Okay, so for that, I have already pushed the file. Okay, so two files I have pushed, how… in whichever way, if you want to use Bedrock models. Okay, just be sure, for that particular user which you are creating in AWS,
Paul: You are, giving the bedrock access for that particular user.
Paul: Okay. So, I think… let me just open GitHub.
Paul: It's somewhere around…
Paul: Lama Index Tutorials, I think this is the one. Okay, so the repo is exactly the same, only two files I have added.
Paul: Okay, so once if you want to use a direct API, or through your AWS credentials, like using secret keys.
Paul: And, only one change?
Paul: You have to install one package.
Paul: Okay, the Bedrock Converse and the Bedrock Employees. These two are the important packages that needs to be installed.
Paul: REST, you have to pass the model name. Okay. And, probably for the embedding, I have used Amazon Titan embeddings. Okay, so whoever wants to look into this Amazon part, they can simply look into. It's just two lines, change of code. REST, everything is fine.
Paul: Alright, direct API means? No, no, nothing proven. How much bandwidth? It's a different service.
Paul: Alright, so let's continue our discussion.
Paul: Okay, so this is the notebook 3 that we'll be discussing already, the notebook 1 and the notebook 2 we have gone through. Okay, and in the last class, I think, we shaved our head around, like.
Paul: 21st, okay, so they're evaluating the ideal chunking size in that class. We have already gone through that particular content. You guys have
Paul: fix it, if you remember. Okay, so that notebook also is available. So today's discussion, it will be for, in, vector store integration with Lama Index.
Paul: Alrighty, please let me know.
Paul: Everyone is ready. I think it is exactly the same notebook. There is no difference.
Paul: Just like last time. So, please let me know that can we continue or not.
Paul: Mohammad is asking, what is Bedrock? It's a service from AWS.
Paul: If we want to use the models through AWS for that specific
Paul: Amit, it's the same one, there has been no change.
Paul: Alright, so let's proceed with our discussion.
Paul: Finally, so…
Paul: Now, in the import part, if you remember in the last task we have gone through.
Paul: Okay, so in the Lama index, now, what is the change in this particular notebook? So here, we'll be just using
Paul: The vectors tools. Okay, so till now, in Langchain, we have gone through that, so this time, as we are discussing Llama Index, okay, so for Llama Index part, we'll be talking. So, two examples that I have taken, so for Chroma and quadrant vectors, okay, and as you can see here, the packages are there.
Paul: So, just be sure, in your requirements, I think everybody has installed it.
Paul: These two packages.
Paul: I think last time, also, these two packages were there, so just be sure these packages are available
Paul: In your virtual environment.
Paul: Alright, so let's proceed.
Paul: Let me just Google.
Paul: This one, okay, and I think it should be visible to everyone.
Paul: Okay, so let's start our discussion. So, from Lama Index School, the vector store index, the simple directory reader, the purpose, so it will simply fetch out the files, and through that, you can read the files. Then comes your settings, which is the most important part.
Paul: In global settings, you define your embedding models, if you remember. Okay, and comes your LLM. Then you have a document.
Paul: Then comes storage context and, load index from storage. Now, load index, at any point of time, if you're saving the index in your local machine, okay, then, it is important.
Paul: Otherwise, we'll be using this majorly the vector store index.
Paul: Now, two things here.
Paul: So, first of all, we are importing the vector store info and the metadata info. This comes from Llama Index score package.
Paul: Then, getting our retriever, the vector index retriever, and the vector index auto retriever. So, both are retriever-based systems. Right now, I can use any one of them. And finally, the query engine.
Paul: Okay? I hope everybody remembers from the last class. Okay.
Paul: No, first of all, I'm just having a check whether the vector store is available or not. And right now, as you can see here, OpenAI embeddings and Hugging Face embeddings are two important ones, so if you don't want to use OpenAI, simply switch to Hugging Face.
Paul: And just be sure the packages are available in your system. So, right now, I will just execute this cell, just to check that all the imports are working good or not. So, I think for everybody, the imports are working.
Paul: Once the imports are done, in the next step, we'll be defining our global settings in the global settings. So, first of all, OpenAI.
Paul: Okay, so here I've specified a model, and then comes your embedding model definition, so both the model definition that I have passed.
Paul: Now, the chunk size and chunk overlap, so this also needs to be defined within your global settings, so these two things that I am passing, so let me…
Paul: Take the configuration here.
Paul: Now, as I have imported documents, so I have taken some test data for now, as you can see here. So, vector DBs, HNSW, okay, some embedding model data, and quadrant data. Now, these are all sample data that I have taken.
Paul: Now, whenever I'm creating a document, two important things, the text and the metadata that comes. So here, a piece of text that I do have, and with that, a metadata, based on, like, topics. So now this is just a sample data that we have created.
Paul: Alright, so 5 sample documents that I have passed. So, first of all, comes the in-memory vector store. If you remember, even in LanChen, this feature was available.
Paul: How many of you remember, in Lanshan?
Paul: The same feature, in-memory vector deal, where you really don't need to actually use a third-party service, the inbuilt ones.
Paul: Now, generally, like, the in-memory vector store is not so much useful, as you know that most of the times, if you're working, you will be using some type of vector table.
Paul: So, right here…
Paul: the vector store index that I am calling, okay, from documents, then I'm passing the set of documents, the 5 documents that I have created.
Paul: Yes, this is only for POC, correct? Okay, and then let's execute this. So here, just I'm calculating the current time with the start time. Okay, then we will know the total time it has taken.
Paul: Okay, so right now,
Paul: I have to… and, for the chunks, I hope everybody remembers, in Llama Index, like, what are the chunks called?
Paul: In the last class, we have discussed.
Paul: nodes, okay? And, any type of chunking algorithm, so that will be basically the node parsing, okay? So, note parsers is the actual import through which you perform your
Paul: Nodes creation or chunk creation.
Paul: Now, I hope till this point, for everybody, it should work, because it's pretty much simple. Now, always remember in-memory vector stores, just like in Langshin, it's only good for POCs. In production, nobody uses them.
Paul: Now, coming to Chroma. In my system, the Chroma package is already installed, so when I executed the, I can say the import section, there I didn't got any error.
Paul: So, first of all, I will initialize my Chroma client. Okay, so here, now, this is how they have defined… okay, they call it, okay, as you can see, deferral client.
Paul: Now, this is in-memory implementation of Chroma. As you noted, every third-party vector database can also have their in-memory implementations.
Paul: And even there is a persistent client also.
Paul: Okay, now this is the in-memory client, and this is the persistent client. So if you want to save the information, so right now I have not do this, but you can simply replace the input, and you can save it
Paul: in your local machine, if you want persistence memory. Very similar implementation, but in Langchen also it's available. Only the import that is changed.
Paul: Hmm… All right.
Paul: Amit is telling, one requirement I corrected in GitHub, Llama, I was missing. Okay, alright. Yes, only two imports, guys, that I have added. Okay, so that, I think, for Bedrock, only that model, whoever wants to test it out.
Paul: So, first of all, I am providing a collection name. If you remember, collection name. Why collection name is important? Because all the
Paul: chunks, or basically the nodes that you will be saving once they are converted into Vector TV. Okay, so that will be within your collection. Now, first of all, I will be creating the collection.
Paul: So, Chroma Client Create Collection, so I'm simply passing the name.
Paul: And then finally, here…
Paul: Chroma collection here. The definition, or basically the collection that I want to actually use for the vector store, that I am passing it here.
Paul: Now, in the next step, you can see Create Storage Context. Okay, now, this storage context, now, this is somewhere new, like, in Langchain, a different name was used. So, if you remember how LanChain, what we will be using.
Paul: Directly, like, from documents?
Paul: If you remember.
Paul: Anybody remembers, like, Foreign Chroma, exactly the syntax?
Paul: Chroma Vector Store and Storage Context.
Paul: Chroma Vector Store is the definition where you are passing in which collection you want to save it.
Paul: And later on, we are actually passing
Paul: Okay, now this is the storage context definition. This is how your Chroma, like, syntactically it has been defined for LAMA mantach.
Paul: Okay, from documents, everybody remembers in Langshan, always remember, because these…
Paul: all these frameworks serves the, I can say, similar functionalities, but only the import changes.
Paul: Now, once I have defined my storage context, okay, now you can see here, so now this storage context that I am passing it here, next is basically the setup documents.
Paul: Now, if you remember, in Langdain, it was much easier in direct one call. But here, first, creating the collection, if you remember, in Langchain, directly, like, this feature was directly enabled here only. Okay, whenever you were doing from documents.
Paul: Okay, but here, directly is not available. Separately, you need to do the definition.
Paul: Yes, it was all in the constructor, correct?
Paul: Now, let me do it. Okay, so I will just, be executing.
Paul: Okay, and right now, based on that, so 5 documents, so how many nodes? So, 5 nodes are there, based on that, 5 indexes that have been created here.
Paul: Now, see, show progress always, like, it is not required, just for visualization I'm showing you, otherwise you can keep this as false. Whenever I'm using it in production, I keep it as false.
Paul: What is storage context?
Paul: storage context. Through storage context, you save the information within the collection in your lab.
Paul: Okay, whoever is asking what is storage context? By default, it is enable line chain, but here, very specifically, you have to define.
Paul: Perfect.
Paul: Now, similarly, for your quadrant vector store, implementation.
Paul: Now, in Quadrant, a very similar feature is available. One is the in-memory implementation.
Paul: Renu Gadivi is asking, kindly share the GitHub with the same GitHub of the last class.
Paul: Now, here, similarly for Quadrant, also, you have the in-memory, implementation. So here, when you define, location is equal to memory. Now, how many of you remember this?
Paul: It seemed as in lynching.
Paul: There is no change here.
Paul: It's the same definition, if you remember, in Lansing.
Paul: Because this is the actual quadrant client that I'm.
Paul: Okay, because… how many of you remember about the quadrant Client client package?
Paul: Anybody remember the Quadrant Client Package?
Paul: Yeah, syntaxes are different, the concept is incorrect.
Paul: but does not have filters. So, no, right now, we are not talking about filters or metadata filtering here. We are simply talking about the implementations.
Paul: So, now, first of all, create the quadrant vector store.
Paul: Here, I'm just calling my quadrant vector store, the client I am passing.
Paul: So through the client, we will know what type of memory definition that needs to be passed. So here, even I have kept it, if you need persistent storage, so majorly, most of the time, you'll be working with persistent, or you use ThreadPad. I hope everybody remembers our… in our project, we have used a cloud cluster of Quadrant, but right now, this is a local implementation.
Paul: Yes?
Paul: So, like, most of the time, two things can happen. You might use a cloud-hosted service, or you might host Quadrant in your own interface.
Paul: So, both the options are available.
Paul: Okay, so whichever way, but your main implementation will always be the same.
Paul: Now, in the next step, as I told you, here, your storage contact needs to be defined for this particular quadrant DV. Okay, so just like your Chroma, a similar definition.
Paul: Now, here, if you, look, so the implementation is same. There is no change in the syntax.
Paul: So, generally, we were starting… I will just do the execution here.
Paul: Okay, now if you really look into the speeds, okay, now this part you can actually focus on. So, quadrant index creation took around 1.95 seconds, and if you really try to compare it with Chroma, Chroma took 1.77.
Paul: Okay, now, can you tell me, like, why…
Paul: Kruma is faster as compared to Quadrant.
Paul: Because, see, it's… the seconds are really small, but why?
Paul: Yes, anybody, if you try to compare.
Paul: So generally, it comes Chroma is then, memory, All right.
Paul: No, no, no, not GraphQL that we are talking about.
Paul: Nothing… I'm using all local here. I'm nothing using any type of remote.
Paul: Chroma is in-memory, for sure, with a C++-based implementation.
Paul: So that's why somehow it's faster.
Paul: Okay, optimized much more.
Paul: Okay, so whereas I feel that Quadrant, it's good, but again, somehow it's toward the lower side, because, if you try to compare Rust with… because in quadrant, a lot of things in the backend are used with Rust. So, really, like, if you try to compare the speeds, somehow I feel C will give you much
Paul: better speeds as compared to Rust.
Paul: For bigger projects, I thought better to go with quadrant, exactly correct. For bigger projects, always use, like, VV8, quadrant, okay, those type of, vector TVs.
Paul: Though, right now, Chroma has launched their enterprise, but again, like, I am not… if you want to make your solutions scalable, not a fan of Chroma. But, for POC, it's really good.
Paul: What parameters tell the project is bigger? Simply the total number of vectors Okay? Always remember.
Paul: AlloyDB is also good, but I have only done the POC, never used it in production again.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: All right, now let's proceed ahead.
Paul: With our embedding model comparison, this time I've kept one
Paul: Now, embedding models. Anybody have used, Voyage models?
Paul: Voyage, embedding models, anybody?
Paul: Voyage AI models… alright, probably in some class, I'll be taking the example. They are also really good, because I tested out the Amazon Titan, they are not really good.
Paul: Okay, like, when I tried to compare them with OpenAI,
Paul: Or, even with some Quen models also.
Paul: This time…
Paul: Alright, now, if you don't have OpenAI, the alternate solution is to go ahead with the hugging Face. This is, I hope everybody remembers.
Paul: This embedding model, the free one.
Paul: having 384 dimensions, because this is the first time I think I'm using all-mini LM in this course.
Paul: Okay, because I think I have used Majorly OpenAI, or you guys might have used Gemini.
Paul: Okay, but this is the alternate free solution that you can always work with.
Paul: Oh, in the next step, okay, now the model will be downloaded. Because of that, it will take some time.
Paul: Right now, this is a local implementation.
Paul: Okay, as you can see here, the dimension is right now 384, so this is just good for learning, it's just like…
Paul: In machine learning, if you have worked with the IBELS data effect, are very similar here. If you are starting your RAC journey, okay, then only we use it.
Paul: Then comes a simple comparison, and really, like, if you want to compare embedding models, how many of you remember about the MTB leaderboard? That is the best place.
Paul: Don't do the research by yourself. Always pick up the top 20 models. Okay, from the top 20 models, pick up the top
Paul: Like, something from 5 in between, like, you can pick up… it's not necessarily the top 5, because few embedding models requires a lot of VRAM, okay? But at least pick somewhere. According to your use case, pick up what will be your budget, at least for one year, and based on that, always decide.
Paul: In Hugging Face, we are doing the downloading of the model exactly correct.
Paul: Now, coming to, persistent storage, so here, as you can see, now I have defined a persistent, storage directory. Okay, now, in this part, if you want to, like, very specifically see
Paul: all of your storage for the vector team implementation. You can change this name, I think I already have the storage one.
Paul: Yeah, so let me just delete.
Paul: All right.
Paul: Now, here, if you really look into what is the main syntax, now, using the storage context that previously you have defined, and through that. Now, this is directly LAMA index…
Paul: implementation. This is not a package-based implementation, guys. Okay, so Lama Index directly gives you this functionality where you can directly save the indexes.
Paul: But I prefer saving indexes through the actual package. So, like.
Paul: if you're using Chroma, always save the indexes through the actual package implementation. I feel it's always safer in that one.
Paul: Alright, now, in the next step, once you have saved in the… you can simply load the index.
Paul: Okay, now loading the index. Now, this is the actual import that we have taken it, from the, import section. Okay, now this needs to be passed, and if you really look into the storage context loaded. Now, this we are defining. So, can you see here, in Langchen, we never handle the storage context.
Paul: But in Llama Index, manually, you have to do the, like, you need to handle the implementation through the storage context. So your storage context becomes the most important thing.
Paul: Okay, so this is somewhere new, if you try to compare it with LanChain.
Paul: It's just one more line that you need to always work with, because the entire aim always happened with the storage context.
Paul: Vishal is asking, what is storage context? Through storage context, you always save the information.
Paul: Now, that is the actual, like, the memory, like, that memory gets transferred into the vector DB. Now, with that storage context, whatever you want to do. It's not necessary that every time you want to save it, rather than if you directly want to have a local, locally, if you want to save it.
Paul: Or, if you want to load up your indexes.
Paul: The same thing, like, storage context was there in LAN channels, but directly, it was predefined, so you really never knew.
Paul: distance.
Paul: Okay, and finally comes your query engine. Okay, because we have already performed the indexing, so in the next step, simply on top of the chroma index that we have saved, we are performing, the query operation.
Paul: Okay, now here, top K and response mode. Let's go with the generic one compact, because in the previous classes, we have gone through the multiple response modes.
Paul: So, first of all, the initialization of the query engine, and then passing my query.
Paul: To the query engine.
Paul: Mohan is exactly the same GitHub in the last class that we have discussed.
Paul: Alright, I think everybody has that GitHub link. If you don't have the GitHub link, Sure.
Paul: Please, at least go through Notion, guys.
Paul: Now I've shared it in the chat.
Paul: Alright, now, based on my query, what are the main vector databases mentioned? Okay, now if you really look into… because we have 5 documents, so you can manually do the verification.
Paul: So, really, let's go into the document.
Paul: Where we have done the definition.
Paul: affected you. Okay, now if you're really looking to know, this is the actual sentence.
Paul: Okay, Quadrant, Pinecone, Viviate, Milverse. Okay, and based on that, if I really look into my…
Paul: a response from the query engine exactly where I put. Okay, so I can say that, yes, it has pulled up the exact information.
Paul: Now,
Paul: See, as I told you, even in the last class, we have gone through multiple response modes. Okay, so now this time, let's try to just execute. Now, here I have defined compact, ready summarize, simple summarize, and refine.
Paul: Now, compact gives you the smallest answer. Tree summarize gives you the longest form of answer that you need, simple summarize. It's bigger than compact, but smaller than tree summarize. And finally, refining. Refining only focus on the core sentences.
Paul: Now, here, if you really look into, compact is coming close to 610 characters. Okay, so here it's simply the comparison of the response modes, just like in last time we have done.
Paul: But I feel that compact is always good when you are looking for your small answers. I feel that this is the best one where you get your entire context. Sometimes in refine, I feel that a lot of noise can also be added.
Paul: Now, let's check. Okay, so here, the compact mode is coming close to 610 characters. Tree summarize, coming to 618. Then comes your simple summarize, the shortest form, I can say, right here.
Paul: Now, most of the times here, if you are looking into the result, it's coming to 588, okay? So, don't think that always these results will be same, but I feel that 3 summarizes the
Paul: one where we get most number of characters. When you will be actually working with real-time data.
Paul: tree summarize, like, whenever I want to write any type of blog, okay, so for that blog.
Paul: If I want to pass 10 different type of sources. At that particular point of time, I feel that TreeSummarize works better as compared to others. So, like, it depends upon the usage that you are selecting, but, like, if I want bigger response, I stick to TreeSummarize.
Paul: Otherwise, the go-to solution is compact. I don't work with refine a lot. It always, the output size increases with the tokens, and if you really look into
Paul: There is not a lot of changes.
Paul: Okay, so the core context to gather out, compact is the best one.
Paul: And why compact?
Paul: Can anybody tell me why Compact is good and mediumly used in Llama Index?
Paul: because of the context window definition for any type of LLM. Context window, every LLM has a context window size. Okay, because of that, we always try to work with much more compact versions, because at the end of the day, your cost can also increase if you're going with bigger versions or the refined versions.
Paul: So, because if the token generation is on the higher side, simply your cost will increase.
Paul: So, I will suggest always try to use, compact or re-summarize. Not a fan of simple summarize, because I feel compact does the job. And refine, it's towards the higher size, and nobody needs, actually, like, more tokens, if you can actually get the core context.
Paul: Now, here, even accumulate is also there, but I have just provided, now, compact, fast and good, general use, tree summarize, longer, context, simple summarize, simple queries, refined, slow, excellent, but high quality needed. So, really, like, whenever you are
Paul: Working with the refined, it always comes with the cost.
Paul: So, you know that every solution, if you're looking for quality, it always comes with a cost.
Paul: Now comes your streaming responses. Now, streaming responses, I really love, doing the implementations whenever you are working, whether in POC. Why?
Paul: Why streaming responses are good.
Paul: dive?
Paul: Streaming responses.
Paul: Character by character, when you say, rather than showing you the full answer in one shot.
Paul: What happens, like, I feel that sometimes the latency can be high.
Paul: Okay, it means that the user might need to wait a long time. Probably, I can say 10 seconds, sometimes 20 seconds. It totally depends upon
Paul: which feature?
Paul: Like, if you are going with higher number of top K chunks, more chunks.
Paul: bigger context window, I can say, which is passed to the LLM, because, the context window, the limit is there. Now, within that context window, your context size becomes really big, so the processing time becomes higher.
Paul: So, because in those cases, I prefer streaming responses, and majorly, every product, if you look into, they show the responses in streaming responses.
Paul: So, always use that.
Paul: Rishi, it's not really to avoid K2B timeouts. In some cases, it happens, but not every time.
Paul: Sanjayth, how to flow the streaming responses, in the UI? In UI, it really depends upon the framework. Okay, like, in Next, Jets, React, you can do it in Streamlit again.
Paul: Through state management, you can pass it.
Paul: If a disconnection is happening, and the retrieve from a specific chunk, If a disconnection happening.
Paul: If a disconnection… what do you mean by disconnection happening? Like, I could not get that monitored.
Paul: Like, streaming, is it more like getting a response as soon as possible? It's not getting a response, it's getting, like, a part of the response. It can be a token or a token generation.
Paul: Okay, so for example, if I show you right here. Now, if you look into the implementation here, so first of all, defining the query engine.
Paul: Okay, and here, just one parameter that needs to be added, which is streaming is equal to true.
Paul: And now, based on that, I think boot syntax error is line number… okay, alright.
Paul: How the hell do I change the syntax?
Paul: Right.
Paul: Okay, can you see here, like,
Paul: This is coming through a streaming part, rather than throwing you that one shot.
Paul: Okay, so I feel that,
Paul: like, this is somehow a better one. From EY perspective, really, for backend developers, it doesn't matter. It's just from the UI side, if you really feel.
Paul: Streaming is like the flow of water from the pipe.
Paul: I really don't think in that way. Streaming means, like, token by token, so… in that way, like, drops of water, like, suddenly however way you want to understand.
Paul: Rahul is asking a chunked response.
Paul: What do you mean here, chunked response? This is a final response, this is not a chunked response. This response is coming from the LL, everyone.
Paul: So users don't face the execution, correct, Ariane? Your intuition? It continuously shows the output, hence the user needs something is coming back and not stuck, exactly correct.
Paul: to avoid modular strut while the user is waiting correct, everyone getting correct implementation. So, whenever you are working in a product.
Paul: Like, this is a requirement generally comes from the UI guys. If…
Paul: You have to understand if the response time is high. And generally, for LLM-based applications, your response will always be on the higher side.
Paul: In production, we don't work only with top 3. It can be sometimes top 10, top 50. So, more the chance.
Paul: higher will be the time for your response generation. Because of that, I feel that this feature is directly implemented.
Paul: Now, in LanChain, okay, so how many have worked? Yeah, because I think… have I shown you the implementation in LanChain?
Paul: The same feature is available, but I feel that Lama Index is much cleaner as compared to this. In Langshan also, the same implementation is available. Later on, probably in our use case, we can look into that.
Paul: Alright, now,
Paul: Let's talk about some custom retriever implementations, I feel that, like, this also can be used sometimes.
Paul: Now, here what I have done is, if you remember the, vector index retriever and the vector index auto retriever. The auto retriever, generally, like, it's in the auto mode, but, right now.
Paul: So, what is the purpose of this vector index retriever? Can anybody tell me?
Paul: One, in one place, you might do a retrieval operation.
Paul: through the actual package, okay? Like, through Chroma also, you can perform a retrieval operation, or, through the Lama Index, or through LangChain core implementation. It means that retrievers are generally available in the core VectorDB packages also.
Paul: It means that the custom implementations of those third-party packages. Or you can do the implementations directly from Llama also.
Paul: Okay, so I've thought about showing you the Llama part, but always try to use the package ones. I feel that it is always safer.
Paul: Yeah, so, like, whenever you are doing in-core functionalities of any type of vector TV,
Paul: try to use the implementations directly from there, because I feel they are much better optimized as compared to doing an implementation in LandChain or in Lama Index.
Paul: Because I have seen, like, when you will actually go for performance and optimization, I feel that Lang Channel Llama Index
Paul: actually drops when you try to scale them up. So always try to take implementations from your core, vector DB. Like, if you have something, take all the implementations from Quadrant. In that way, it's always
Paul: to the better side. If you feel, take the implementations from Chroma, or Melbours, or from WebGate, rather than using the default one from LanChain or Llama.
Paul: When you really need the custom, I really look at…
Paul: You don't need the custom, I'm just showing you.
Paul: the implementation, yeah.
Paul: So,
Paul: like, again, so in the vector index retriever, so previously I've defined the chroma index, I'm simply passing it, and then the similarity, topK is equal to 3 that I have defined.
Paul: Now, coming to the query string that I'll be passing, okay, then I will be retrieving my query notes, or basically my retrieval nodes from that vector TV.
Paul: So, let me just execute that.
Paul: Now, directly, I'm not passing any query engines, so it's basically… right now, I'm looking into the node 1, Node 2, and the Node 3 implementation.
Paul: So, based on the query, whatever query that I have passed, now, if you remember a very similar implementation, we have done it in the last class also.
Paul: Now, if you remember, so whenever we are doing a retrieval, in Langshan, there are two. One is a default retrieval, and then comes a default width score.
Paul: The similarity score. Two different implementations are there.
Paul: In Llama, through the default one only, you can get this code. So this is the actual similarities code that you have, and through that, you can actually
Paul: like, get the results. I feel that, the iterable part is better and keener in Llama, and easier to implement if you really try to compare it.
Paul: Alright, MMR part I'm not going to show you now, because right now I'm not working with MMR here.
Paul: Alright, now, similar, now, the…
Paul: Building the query engine from the custom retriever.
Paul: So, retriever part, so the previous retriever that I have already defined, and this is somewhere new, the retriever query engine.
Paul: Now, let's try to get this. Now, this is a custom retrieval query engine that you have defined. I think everybody understands what is the query engine in Llama Index, through which you actually generate your LLM responses.
Paul: Okay, so here, during the… Custom Query Engine Retriever on top of our
Paul: custom one. So, you can actually define your custom retrievers. Now, really, like, I feel that sometimes only it is important, always working with retrieval with Square Engine, it's not required.
Paul: Okay, but an added functionality if you want to, really. Now, custom query engine retrievers, where it will be very, very important.
Paul: In LanChain, if you guys remember, if you're working with
Paul: 4 to 5 different types of retrievers. It can be external-based retrievers also, like some, packages like Table, Wikipedia, Archive.
Paul: In those cases, having a custom, retriever implementation, within that custom retriever, if you want to keep, like, 4 to 5 retrievers, it's really good, rather than always, calling each retriever in each shot.
Paul: So, in those cases only, I feel it is important, but if you have a single query engine, okay, for a single retriever, really, it doesn't make sense to all, work with a custom query engine.
Paul: Now comes your natural language metadata filtering. Okay, now if you remember, a very similar implementation we have gone in Lansion also. So, a simple example that I have kept it here.
Paul: So, first of all, this is a metadata info definition that we are doing, okay? And, where have I defined?
Paul: this one.
Paul: Can anybody tell me?
Paul: Yes.
Paul: Can you see here the description? Now, this description sometimes can be AI-generated also.
Paul: Because I prefer much more AI-generated, descriptions in your metadata, but that comes always with the cost.
Paul: Because exactly what is there within your chunk, for every chunk, manually, it is not possible. Most of the time, we use AI. So, here, right now, I've taken simple three fields, the name, type, and the description, where I've defined, okay, and let's try to apply
Paul: So here, I have taken an auto-retriever part, where I pass the vector store info. Now, if you remember, this is the vector store info.
Paul: This is not the vector store index.
Paul: Both the things are different. Index means your actual information.
Paul: Okay? And the vector store info, when I'm talking about. It needs the information about your, chance.
Paul: within the vector store.
Paul: two separate things. Vector store index is separate, and the vector store info is separate.
Paul: Okay, so if you want your manual custom data to be added, then in those type of implementations, like vector store info, I feel it's safer to always work with.
Paul: Alright, now, Here, I have defined mine.
Paul: And so here, I've just done the initialization of the vector index auto-retriever. So previously, auto-retrievers are good when you have very
Paul: good quality of metadata. Previously, we have not defined, but this time I've defined the metadata. So, this particular metadata, vector store info, I am actually
Paul: passing it to the auto-retriever. I can say initialization as an index, and through that, let me just call it…
Paul: So… let me… take a query.
Paul: So here, based on that, so I have passed a string query.
Paul: Alright, now, directly on top of that, I am calling my auto-retriever object.
Paul: Okay, and this auto-retriever object, I am doing a retrieval where I'm passing the string query. And based on that, I'm getting… these are my retrieve contexts. Now, I'm not using any query engine. The idea was to fetch the nodes or the chance.
Paul: Now, when to use vector index auto-retriever?
Paul: I feel that, by default.
Paul: you should always use a vector index auto retriever, rather than always going for the default one, which is the vector index retriever.
Paul: The Auto Retriever, directly fetches the information through metadata and gives… always gives you better results.
Paul: So, if you really look into the auto-retriever advantages, so LLM extract metadata filters from your NL query. Okay, applies filters to your vector stores and perform, simility search. Now, I feel that this implementation is better. It gives you always…
Paul: Like, better results as compared to your mean vector.
Paul: index retriever. Now, vector index retriever, it means that it's the vanilla flavor, okay? It means that really doesn't check up, with the other features, but really, that LLM extracts the metadata filter, so this is where it gives much more added information to the elements.
Paul: Now, see, we always send our chunk information to the LLM, yes or no?
Paul: Do you think that you sent your metadata information?
Paul: to the LLM? Just think.
Paul: Okay. Now, as you see, whenever you are working with chunks, there are so many research papers.
Paul: In some research papers, they have proven that if you keep your metadata information within the chunk, okay, somehow, they got better results.
Paul: Okay, now, really, like, I've seen in very few implementations doing that. Okay, so in that case, rather than keeping my metadata information always within the actual chunk information.
Paul: I feel that if you can pass it, so through Auto Retriever, okay, you can actually pass that information. So, really, I feel that this is powerful as compared to the vanilla implementation of Langchain.
Paul: Now, metadata is not only for filtering.
Paul: Actually, Melind metadata can be used to give better context to the LN.
Paul: Because when you are passing some information, your actual context with the metadata, it gets more information about that.
Paul: So it's not necessary that… see, the…
Paul: There are multiple purposes of using metadata. It's not only that filters, or filtering on top of that, or making your query much more optimized, yes, those are features, but multiple uses are.
Paul: So, like, metadata… that's why I told you in so many classes, you should have very good and vibrant quality of metadata. Better the metadata schema that you propose before starting your solution, because going forward, you might increase it.
Paul: Okay, you can keep some fields LAN and NAN, not to worry about, but later on, when you actually make your solution much… your solution bigger and bigger, when your vectors reach billions in production.
Paul: In those cases, it's really, really important.
Paul: Alright, so… few implementations of Llama. Okay, now, because I will keep this part till here only.
Paul: advanced literal parts and a few other things we'll be talking about probably, like, tomorrow.
Paul: I've thought about showing you some implementations in mixed way, because from tomorrow's class, it will be the actual advanced track that I will start.
Paul: Now, these are all the basics of Llama. Now, it's totally up to you, like, whichever way, if you want to use with lanching or with, Lama Intex.
Paul: My personal choice for beginners, stick to LanChain. For power users, use Rama Index.
Paul: Because I feel in…
Paul: you will be… you will be working with LamaPars a lot. In production, people are using Lama Parse, really, like, most of them are working with LamaPars.
Paul: So, whenever, like, we are working with Llama parts, I prefer to work with Llama Index much more.
Paul: Alright, now I think this part is done, I will just save the information.
Paul: R-ranking, we will come. Deva, it's not like in one. R-ranking is part of advanced rank, okay?
Paul: So I think, here, like, hybrid, search, re-ranking, ID, these concepts will start from the next class, not too well.
Paul: Now, like, I was…
Paul: Once we have discussed these three topics, then actually, I'll be asking you to work on your project, so create a team and start working. I'll be sharing,
Paul: Basically, I will be sharing what are the requirements from my site and architecture summary, and the idea is you start working at least with one cloud platform.
Paul: Because in the last class, few people told that they want to go with that AWS certification, so I feel that, working with a full stack of AWS RAT, it can be helpful to a few people.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: So, I'll be talking about that in the next class, but now we will start with, Chang Jingman.
Paul: There, I'll only be taking
Paul: GoAge AI, Viraj, can you please share GoAge AI? What is GoAge AI?
Paul: I've not worked with GoAge AI, really. Like, I have to search about GoHage.
Paul: Okay, Voye, okay, Vo… no, no, no, Voya is directly available. It's…
Paul: I've seen the trend people are shifting to GoAge AI embeddings earlier, like, in the past 3 months.
Paul: The sizable idea.
Paul: Okay, so… This is from, Mongo, as you can see, this product. People are actually using it.
Paul: Because, like, I know most of them are working with MongoDB. Okay, so the billing part and other things, they get cheaper. And many people are using Mongo in production, so they are actually sticking to, like, VoIJ.
Paul: Okay, so, like, if you want to go through, you can check, I have shared the link.
Paul: It's… generally, they provide, good embedding models.
Paul: Alright, so this part is done, now the next part, little bit with chunking that we'll be talking about.
Paul: So, I think, first of all, let me get the repo of chunking.
Paul: the tub…
Paul: Oof… Chonky junkers, okay?
Paul: Alright, so this will be the next repo that we'll be talking about, so you guys can take a clone of this repo.
Paul: No… We'll be going through Chomky and the Chomky documentations directly from
Paul: like, this is one of the best libraries, I prefer to use it in…
Paul: Production, rather than always picking up lynchin, or like, Llama.
Paul: Okay, I feel that for your general chunking purpose, Chongcare is one of the best ones.
Paul: And everybody is using it, and I've seen this project, I even know the developer, okay, who is the lead, he is building the product.
Paul: Even you guys can get connected to him, Reddit.
Paul: I started to saw, like, starting from only 3 stars or 4 stars, and right now this project has really gone.
Paul: Really, one of… one of the good projects
Paul: Because for every, I can say component I prefer to use a…
Paul: separate library or a separate framework. In that way, I can always create separate microservices
Paul: I feel that this is really good.
Paul: Everybody please take a clone of this.
Paul: And then we will start with chunking. Little bit of chunking, why chunking, those type of things.
Paul: Oh, boy.
Paul: So I'm giving you two to three minutes, everybody take the clones, set up the report.
Paul: And I think, the… ENV5 is also there, so it will be easier to do the setup.
Paul: I think very chonky, yes, this is a chonky… Great move data… A requirement…
Paul: All right, yes. So, please do the installation. Create the environment, and please do the installation.
Paul: Sharon is asking players to do one video. These are models, Sharon. Only one line change.
Paul: For everything, working with videos, It's just a script, only one line of change in your embedding model definition.
Paul: Okay, Anne, please…
Paul: Check the implementation of Bedrock. Like, in the last few people asked about Bedrock, so I've shared the test script, so simply check the test script. This is a simple test script, and really, like, two lines of definition. I think in one place, I've used… worked with DeepSeek.
Paul: This is the API part, and I hope everybody understands the API.
Paul: Like, I don't know how many of you know about this, but let me just show you an AWS console once.
Paul: Where is that AWS console?
Paul: Just wait, let me get the authentication code from my authenticator.
Paul: Hmm… Good evening.
Paul: Don't do this? Okay, this has not stored.
Paul: Alright, so, as you can see, this is the AWS console.
Paul: Okay, so from here, just be sure you have a user created.
Paul: Okay, so, for example, a single user, and just be sure.
Paul: you have, permission. So, very specifically, I'm… I was using the AWS Bedrock. I've given you full access, or you can give an… you can give granular level access also.
Paul: Now, here, two things. Like, access keys, you know. So, access keys-based implementation, like, I think everybody knows about access keys. In the project, also, we have worked with access keys. Now, that implementation is this one, test underscore bedrock.
Paul: Okay, now, for this, you have to do the configuration of the AWS CLI, but if you want to go for, like, this one, API keys for Amazon Bedrock. Okay, so for these API keys-based implementation, okay, the API key script is there that I have provided.
Paul: So, simply do the testing from here. And, for me, I was working with
Paul: Bedrock, so let me just open Bedrock.
Paul: Okay, so here, you can actually look into the model catalog. A lot of models are available.
Paul: So, here you can see, like, modality-based, like, embedding models, image, speech, tablet, different ones. So, like, Nova to Sonic, Wastro, Claude models are available. You can get the model providers.
Paul: Okay, or LLM providers and the emitting providers, according to so many organizations are available here.
Paul: Assembly, you can, select it.
Paul: Now, the core part is selecting the model name. Now, in whichever way, for example, if you're working with… now, this is the actual model ID.
Paul: Now, this model ID actually needs to be passed.
Paul: Okay? Now, here, what I have passed, this I got from the inference profiles, because cross-region inference from here, like, if you want to work with deep-seq models, like one that I have selected.
Paul: So you will be getting this inference profile ID, or the inference profile AR.
Paul: Okay, so just copy this. You can copy any one. You can pick up the profile ARN or the profile ID. So I have… both can be used, and just be sure you are passing it in the model.
Paul: Rest, everything is same. You really don't need to change anything.
Paul: This is only for Bedrock users.
Paul: If you're really interested.
Paul: Okay, so just be sure you are not passing the model ID directory, but you are passing the inference profile ID or the inference profile ER.
Paul: Alright, so I was testing… I passed here tooth and…
Paul: In one place, I have used Anthropic Clot Sonnet.
Paul: And, for embeddings, I picked up here Amazon Titan, so you can play different, or you can test different type of models. So really, this is good.
Paul: Amars Sinivar is asking, suppose we want to give UI, and select multiple better-off model passing by. Is there a boilerplate? It's a simple, condition. Like, in stream lit you can do, or through, parameters of your API routes, you can do that, Amhar Sinibar.
Paul: Okay, it's through the API call, the selection of the model. Okay, or if you want to give a drop-down in the backend, just create a symbol. So, that can be handled through FastAPI Easy.
Paul: So whatever the request, in the body of the request, you can keep that, whichever model that is getting selected from the UI, take that as an input from the…
Paul: because, from, like, after next week, I'll be, like,
Paul: just, picking up a good thing. Like, it's not… the project is not for everybody. The idea is that start creating communities within your batch. In that way, you people will also be connected.
Paul: In future, okay, so, like, in that way, I'll be keeping one architect.
Paul: Like, a few developers, just like a team.
Paul: to conduct.
Paul: Once we have covered this hybrid search highly, then we'll be doing the team formation.
Paul: And really, there, only I'll be providing the architecture, rest of the implementation will be entirely from your side. Will be that, project. I know a few people know JWS in a very, very good way.
Paul: Okay, so… I'll be just allocating them, so that at least they can do the supervision of that.
Paul: If you don't know AWS, then I won't be picking up, for sure.
Paul: Only people with AWS only.
Paul: Alright, yeah.
Paul: Please let me know that, part you guys have done it on.
Paul: Cloning and other things from there.
Paul: what will be the criteria I will be selecting, because I know who knows and who don't, that's why.
Paul: Only for developers, it can be, like, anybody can take it.
Paul: But, like, developers can be anybody, but there will be a specific team, like, only 5 to 10 people from the batch. Project managers, probably 2 guys that I will be selecting.
Paul: And I have to look into that, whether they can put at each 30 minutes or 1 hour in a week.
Paul: I have to ask personally.
Paul: Okay. Setup is done, Rajat, alright, after uninstalling, pip uninstalled TensorFlow Media Pipe, all right.
Paul: Worked. We've uninstalled TensorFlow in MediaPike.
Paul: Please check Notion, the email ID is there, and multiple times I have told it.
Paul: at the red question I noted.
Paul: Alright guys, the setup is done, I think, so… let me just close the folder here.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: Alright, before jumping here, okay, so I will just open my notes, and let's try to understand some fundamental things about Chung.
Paul: Okay, so why chunking and those type of stuff?
Paul: Just quit, I will start sharing my iPad.
Paul: So, are the phones with iPad via cable… Perfect.
Paul: I think everybody can see the iPad screen, just provide a confirmation.
Paul: Alright, so first of all, let's try to understand the simplest form, because a lot of chunkers are there.
Paul: Okay, so their implementation is pretty much direct here for single call, but we will try to go inside them, and we will try to understand.
Paul: So, first of all, whenever you are talking with respect to Champi… Okay, so let's try to understand…
Paul: Care Chunkie.
Paul: Now, why we do chunking?
Paul: Because what is the main purpose of doing chunk?
Paul: You guys have done chunking so many times, so what is the purpose?
Paul: Okay, few people are telling, alright, okay. So, limited context window.
Paul: This you have to always remember.
Paul: This is basically the main purpose.
Paul: A limited context wind.
Paul: Now, whenever you are doing chunking, it has to be based on certain conditions.
Paul: Okay, and generally, the conditions that we do follow, it can be based on size.
Paul: It can be based on content.
Paul: Or simply, I can say, boundaries.
Paul: Yes, certain type of logic that we may apply, because majorly, like, you guys have already looked into, like, fixed, like, token chunkers, sentence chunkers, those implementations even in Lanshan, I have shown.
Paul: And I told you in Langchen, like, the recursive character, text splitter is one of the best. So, similarly, here also in chunky, it is available. We have to always respect, that whenever you are doing chunking, so you have to pick up the parameters, or certain conditions. It can be based on size, it can be based on the content type.
Paul: Okay, or, like, some type of boundaries. Now, here, the boundaries, very specifically, as we'll be starting our semantic discussion here. So, yes, it can be semantic or non-semantic also.
Paul: Okay, so boundaries can be semantic as well as non-semantic.
Paul: Now, in RAG, whenever we are doing something, okay, now, as we know that
Paul: Giving, the LLM enough context to create useful answers, or create useful responses.
Paul: So… what is the first major one? Like, why we use chunking in the rack?
Paul: Can I say that optimizing
Paul: Your retrieval accuracy? Yes or no?
Paul: The first one.
Paul: you want to get better results. Now, whenever you are doing some type of optimization on top of the retrieval accuracy.
Paul: So, two things. Generally, if I start in chunking, like, two things can happen. Can I say that your chunks can be large, or your chunks can be small? If your chunks are large, then what is the problem that we do face?
Paul: with large chunks.
Paul: Okay, one is large, and let's take another one as small.
Paul: Generally, when the chunks are large, we can say that multiple ideas, or multiple type of context, or multiple type of topics, or subtopics can be mixed together.
Paul: Yes?
Paul: If your chunk is large, can I say that? Like, mixing, in simple terms, I will say.
Paul: mixing of multiple ideas. Multiple ideas when I'm speaking, just be sure it can be, like, topics, subtopics.
Paul: Okay, simply. Like, a lot of information that you are actually passing.
Paul: Now, whenever you're working with largest chunks, what is the main problem that we do face? Noise and jitter, always around.
Paul: noise and jitter. So, generally, we don't perform working with large chunk sizes. So, I don't suggest anything to go beyond 2,000.
Paul: Like, my chunk size… Okay, like…
Paul: 2000 is never my selection. Anything more than 2,000.
Paul: Okay? Like, it should be always less than 2,000.
Paul: Even I prefer somewhere around my preferable number, I told you.
Paul: Between these numbers. It really works good.
Paul: Now, the question comes, like, I hope everybody understands why noise and jitter comes.
Paul: Because if you try to pass too much of context.
Paul: Okay, then what is the exact, or basically the relevant context? It becomes much harder to find for any type of your retrieval algorithm. Whenever you are performing that vector retrieval, it becomes much harder to find the exact relevant context.
Paul: With respect to small ones. Now, why smalls are good? Because they are much focused.
Paul: Always remember. And they try to capture, like, a single idea.
Paul: Now, whenever you are working with smaller chunks, I can see that the quality of the embeddings will always be better.
Paul: Okay, so I can say, like, precise embeddings.
Paul: Whereas, with respect to large, I cannot say the quality of the embeddings will be very, very good on. I will come to this embedding part later on when I'll be talking with respect to pooling. There is a very important concept of pooling. How many of you know pooling?
Paul: Any… anytime you guys have learned.
Paul: anywhere in deep learning, most of you might have learned during CNNs, the concept of pooling, like max pool, mean pool, average pool, okay? Similarly. It's not, PWLN, okay? I'll be coming to that concept, so there we'll be talking about, so when you are actually, generating the embeddings, in those cases.
Paul: like, the quality of the embedding degrades if the chunk is really large. So, we often try to work with small and focused chunks much more.
Paul: Now, this is the first reason that we do prefer. Now, let's try to… Get the second one.
Paul: What is the second reason that we do Chanti?
Paul: One is optimizing. What is the second one, guys? Anything, just say something random.
Paul: Okay? Preserving the context for generation, this is the most important part.
Paul: Opera.
Paul: Always remember.
Paul: Amit is saying not to lose context, correct. Okay?
Paul: This is the main thing, like, this, like, without the, without preserving the context of it, how will we be doing the generation? To generate something, you need context, so this is the most important thing.
Paul: That's why chunking is very, very important.
Paul: Because, like, every time, whenever you are building a RAT, you will say that, find the top 3 chunks, or basically the best chunks, according to the query that you have passed.
Paul: Now, here also are very similar things, so whenever you are working with preserving context for a generation. Now, here also think in that way, if your chunks are too small, or if your chunks are too large.
Paul: So, what will happen if the chunks are very small? Okay, like, let's take the example of too small.
Paul: Look at this same… Too small?
Paul: Too big.
Paul: What will happen if the chunks are too small? So, let's take an example. From a random research paper, you just pick up a single sentence from the middle of the research paper.
Paul: Okay, so do you think that the LLM will understand?
Paul: Okay, so it means that even humans cannot understand, so how the LLM will understand.
Paul: So, I can say that if your chunks are, like, very, very small, then the problem happens that you will always lose context. It's not about losing context, you won't have the context.
Paul: Because here, nothing we are using. Okay, so always remember, you will be having very less context.
Paul: that becomes a problem. So, too small is also a problem.
Paul: And if I'm talking about too big.
Paul: Now, if I'm talking about too big, then what will happen?
Paul: Two big mints, again, the same problem, noise will come.
Paul: Now, in LLMs, if you remember, there is something called as Attention mechanism.
Paul: Okay, now, attention mechanism, always focus, okay, on a particular, I can say, a particular context wing.
Paul: Okay, now, when… it's not exactly a context window, but you can think about a specific piece of text. It always focuses on. When you try to provide
Paul: bigger and bigger context. Okay, then we feel the problem of Attention dilution. Always remember.
Paul: Attention dilution.
Paul: Okay, and sometimes this particular… in some research paper, it is referred to as lost in the middle effect.
Paul: Okay, in academic papers, you'll be getting this term, like, lost in the middle effect or attention dilution.
Paul: Okay, now, in simple terms, what is attention dilution or lost in the middle effect? It means that the LLM, or basically that transformer model, has trouble accessing the information which is buried in the middle of the long context.
Paul: Okay? So, like, trouble?
Paul: accessing… the information…
Paul: Okay? Now, this is a very, very common problem. Too much data, it means that, yes.
Paul: Very similar implementation.
Paul: The idea is Sanket, correct, okay? Lost in the middle can also happen if you are giving large prompt also. Correct.
Paul: But, if you're providing structured large prompt, then it doesn't happen. If there is no structured definition, then it happens. All right, now we're talking about chunking. So, like, this is a very, very common problem. Like, it's a fundamental problem you have to think about. It's within the architecture.
Paul: So, nothing we can do.
Paul: If there is a fundamental problem, so it…
Paul: What is the solution? To change the architecture of transforms?
Paul: So, thought that multiple type of attentions has been brought.
Paul: Okay, right now, after 2023, but for now, if I just focus on the poor retention mechanism.
Paul: Okay, I hope everybody understands the actual technical problem from the architecture perspective of a transformer.
Paul: Like, why it happens. Because if you really try to access some type of information, and which is actually in the middle of a long context, really it cannot handle.
Paul: Okay, and most of the times, your context length will always increase.
Paul: Okay, and the model's attention will always spread.
Paul: And if your model attention gets spread, it becomes harder for the model to fetch.
Paul: The more relevant tasks.
Paul: Okay, so always remember, like, if the model attention always spread across your large context input, okay, it will always provide you less accurate or less relevant information.
Paul: Which will cause more errors in simple terms, okay? More errors, probably, in terms of reasoning also you can think about, or probably it might hallucinate also.
Paul: So, like, just remember the problems. So here, I will just keep hallucinating, because you people have been.
Paul: Using this term a lot.
Paul: Okay, hallucinating, or even with respect to reasoning off.
Paul: Like, these are some core and fundamental problems, and really, if you think from the idea or the core architecture of an LLM, so the problem is there, so nothing that we can do. All we can do is change the architecture of the LLM.
Paul: But you know that it is not possible.
Paul: At least, like, in advanced stage, really, you can change that, but not for now. We are taking it.
Paul: Now, so somewhere we need to work with that.
Paul: Sweet spot. Okay, now, really, like, you need to find that. Nobody knows what is the sweet spot.
Paul: So, whenever I'm talking from the…
Paul: sweet, spot. Okay, it means that, all those things that we have discussed, it means that improving the retrieval quality, so there has to be a balance.
Paul: Okay, then coming managing the LLM context window. Again, the balance has to be there. Then reducing the hallucinations.
Paul: enhancing the efficiency and reducing the cost. These are, like, few parameters that you can think about, the sweet spot. So, like, with respect to cost optimization, I can say direct.
Paul: Yeah, of course.
Paul: Take care of these things.
Paul: Now, generally, nobody thinks about, so these are just, like, parameters, and whenever you are selecting your chunking algorithm, always try to perform this hyperparameters
Paul: Okay, and based on that, select, like, which one works in your use case.
Paul: Then comes managing, the… Llm context window.
Paul: Okay, then comes reducing hallucination.
Paul: And the fourth one is, like, improving your retrievable quality.
Paul: Now, you have to understand all these factors that I have written here.
Paul: Do you think that they are only just because of Chanti?
Paul: Like, reducing hallucination, you have to understand.
Paul: If you're working, if you're not working with a very good LLM, or a low-quality LLM in simple terms, you will face the problem.
Paul: So, don't think about all these problems, or basically, if you are trying to find the sweet spot for your chunking. I cannot say that only they are dependent on chunking. There can be other factors also that might come.
Paul: Into picture.
Paul: Just think about managing the LLM context render if your LLM has a very small context window. Nothing you can do. So, it means that now comes to the selection of the LLM also. Now, improving the retrieval quality, you know that
Paul: Till now, we have worked with dense search, okay, or vector search in simple terms. Probably, like, how to do that, I have to, probably bring,
Paul: some type of, like, sparse vector search, or, like, BM25 algorithm, which will help me to get much more semantic-based some sort.
Paul: So, all these factors that I have told you, King, they are not only for chanting, there are other factors that it can be dependent on. But I'm telling you that always focus on these things.
Paul: Okay, like, I feel that somewhere around, you can pick up the sweet spot here.
Paul: She has even embedding model, like, so many hyperparameters in track, because here everything is a hyperparameter, what you select.
Paul: So, pretty much plug-and-play component. You can change one thing and build from that.
Paul: Now, always remember chunking, so whenever you are doing chunking, because previously it was not mentioned, but right now.
Paul: chunking?
Paul: is part… Oh.
Paul: Context engineering.
Paul: Always remember this.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: Chunking this.
Paul: a part of context engineering. It means that
Paul: You are trying to improve the context that will be fetched.
Paul: Okay, so, previously in, like, back in 2023 and 2024, people, they have not really mentioned, but starting from 2025, they have simply told, okay? Like, chunking is one of the major part of context engineering.
Paul: Because you are actually preparing the input.
Paul: Okay? For the LL, so that it can understand and generate correct responses.
Paul: Alright, so, little bit query that we have gone through, so always remember these few terms, and always try to explain, like in interviews. I've seen in interviews, nobody actually talks from the transformer architecture.
Paul: Prospect. Okay, so always try to bring that prospect also. Okay, and these problems of attention due to dilution.
Paul: Major interviews that I have taken, nobody says about these things, but always try to keep this once in your interview.
Paul: So, Cheta, I always get confused between text splitters
Paul: JTN text splitters are basically the chunkers only.
Paul: Okay, now, how chunking? So, for that, will we apply some type of chunkers. Okay, so, same thing. Text splitters and chunkers. Don't get confused.
Paul: Alright, so let's go for a break, and then, we will start with the rest part, I think. What's the time? Okay, it's 10.30, so let's go for a break.
Paul: Start the clock. Guys, 10 minutes break or 15 minutes break, please let me know.
Paul: Alright, people are telling… 10 minutes, I'm going at, majorly people are telling 10 today.
Paul: I think this is my desktop tool.
Paul: Fine. Okay, so I'll be back in 10 after my breakfast, so you guys also do…
Paul: Yeah, I think everyone is back, please let me know in the chats.
Paul: What about others? Okay, yeah.
Paul: Alright, fine. Okay, so a little bit we…
Paul: Gone. Okay, so now let's try to look into some practical spot.
Paul: Alright, I think before that, where are the chunky dogs?
Paul: All right, now we will start with the practical part. Before that, a little bit about the framework or the library that we'll be working with. So you can see a lightweight ingestion library for fast, efficient, and robust rack pipelines.
Paul: Okay, so pretty much, like, feature is GV to use, wide support, versatile, Okay.
Paul: So, a few things are there. Now, let's focus on the core open source part. So, from here, I will move to the open source.
Paul: And from here, I'll be just looking into this chunkers.
Paul: So now, these are the chunkers, that, for the practical implementation, we'll be looking.
Paul: Now, the first one, if you look into Token Chunker.
Paul: Split text into fit-sized token chunks, best for maintaining consistent chunk size and working with token-based ones.
Paul: Now, token chunkers, I think you guys have already worked with. Yes or no?
Paul: in Lancin.
Paul: Token chunking is also called as fixed size chunking. In lanchine, the term which is used, which is fixed size chunking.
Paul: Yes, okay, the same, the name can be different, but don't, get confused. So, in chonky, the term token chunker is used, but, majorly, like, it's called as thick size chunk.
Paul: Okay, so split the text into fake size token based for maintaining. Now, let's look and start with our practical implementation.
Paul: Alright, so let me first of all check that whether all the imports are working correctly or not.
Paul: So, currently, I'm working with the chunky version, 1.5. Okay, so some of you can test with the latest version.
Paul: Okay, the latest version is 1.5.1, okay.
Paul: Like, when I was creating the content, it was around December 16th, but you can test it, I think.
Paul: Most of the things would work.
Paul: Now, here, I have kept the Gemini API key, okay, or you can work with the OpenAI API key also.
Paul: So, So, I think in my environment variable…
Paul: Belote example. Alright, you have the Gemini API key. I think everybody has the Gemini API key, this is the free one.
Paul: Yes, I'm…
Paul: Damn.
Paul: Now, first of all, if you look into the imports, so in this pretty much simple imports, there is nothing new.
Paul: I have taken this SNS, just I'll be plotting few things.
Paul: Just to give you the idea, that, how to look into the mean standard deviation for those things. Now, if you're working with OpenAI, so simply pass here OpenAI embeddings, and the list of embeddings, I think it's really long here, which is provided.
Paul: Shongy, I think, somehow it will be there. Just wait.
Paul: Okay, so here you can see the embeddings overview, and from here you can see the support
Paul: For different type of emittance.
Paul: If…
Paul: Azure OpenAI, Azure OpenAI is their model to work, GINA embeddings, Gemini, WAJI is also there, Kohar embeddings. Majority, I can say the most commonly used embeddings are there. Otherwise, you can work with your custom embeddings, as always.
Paul: Like, genome embeddings are also good, and you can work with them. Sentence transformers, so this is the model. Okay, so… the implementation is really simple. Okay, we'll just take the specific input.
Paul: Always remember, for every type of embedding when you are doing the implementation, please do check the input.
Paul: Okay, so in our case, we are working with Gemini Impinence. So, for this, you have this particular package, okay, Chonky.
Paul: Okay, now Chonky Gemini should be installed in your system.
Paul: Now, when you just installed Chonky, you might not get all the features.
Paul: Always remember, so whenever you are working with, just be sure you are installing that specific version also.
Paul: So, please do have a check on your import, so now, in the next step. So, from Chonky, imports Gemini embeddings.
Paul: embeddings here, I'm passing the name of the model, the API key, and the task type, which is semantic similarity. Right now, we want to perform. So here you can see the task type has been defined.
Paul: Okay, and based on that, if you try to pass some text, so directly this initialization that I have done, embeddings.embed, and you are passing the text. And based on that, your embedding will take place. So let us check, because my API key, sometimes it works, and sometimes it doesn't.
Paul: Okay, so I can see that, yes, it's working right now.
Paul: So now,
Paul: So, here are some data files that I have provided. Please do load them up. In your case, I think… in my case, the folder is data. In your case, the folder will be new underscore data.
Paul: please have a check on this, otherwise you might get an error. Okay, and you might say that. Okay, so I think everybody can fix this by yourself. You have to just change the path.
Paul: And just be sure you have loaded this up. Yes, I can see here. I've taken simple docs, research, okay, code sample and a table sample representation. So please change the imports, and just be sure you have passed any data, and don't tell me I'm getting an error. I think you people are smart to do that. Yes?
Paul: And people working with OpenAI, please change this to OpenAI embeddings.
Paul: Take one minute, do the configuration, let me know in the chat.
Paul: Down on work.
Paul: Yes, those are document-specific, Ravi, so in that case, I can say markdown text better is better. And generally, for markdown documents, recursive character text better all, like, also works.
Paul: If you look into the logic, actually, for, like, markdown, text bitter, it is actually based on the implementation of recursive character text bitter only.
Paul: Please let me know everybody has configured their embeddings.
Paul: Chunky as a framework only for Chunky.
Paul: And nothing… Okay.
Paul: With chunking, a few other things are also available, but right now, our major focus will be on Chanking.
Paul: 80% of the features are from the chunking side, 20% features are rather there, like vectorDB integration, because at the end of the day, once you have created the chunk, you will create the embeddings, okay, so those type of integrations. But the focus is on chunking only.
Paul: If you are getting import error, please try to solve. Don't ask me right now.
Paul: It's strongly used in production, yes?
Paul: Chunky use tools in production.
Paul: Now, which version of NumPy I am using?
Paul: Even I don't remember, I have to check.
Paul: I'm using version 2.4.
Paul: Alright, now let's start.
Paul: So, I think everybody has loaded up the documents and set their,
Paul: Basically loaded up the documents and set their embedding models.
Paul: me as Shonge… Will work with any framework.
Paul: Okay, now, a few helper functions I have, kept. Okay, the idea is to display the chumps.
Paul: So here, a few things that I've kept, like, just to show you the jumps, one, the chunking has been done. So for that, a simple helper function or a utility function.
Paul: And the other one is basically to do a visualization.
Paul: Okay, for every chunk operation that we'll be doing, because right now, multiple chunking strategies will be discussing. The idea is to show you the chunk size distribution through plots.
Paul: And what is the meaning through that? Because, actually, when you are working in a chunking module, those statistics data also we do save sometimes. So, for that, I've kept the information.
Paul: Alright, so… AS Summit, please do that installation.
Paul: Okay, so anybody working with, just be sure you have installed the appropriate package, okay, and that information, you'll be getting it here.
Paul: Perfect, now…
Paul: Okay, so just wait. Okay, now, this is the standard mean deviation fine. Then comes comparing the chunkers.
Paul: Product.
Paul: And Let me just load it up.
Paul: Alright, for the first one, the chunkers that we have, okay, so here is basically the token chunker. And always look into the API reference documentation, because this library, as you can see, though it has become stable, I've worked with it
Paul: For the past 6 to 8 months, so I know that it gets updated, so in the syntax, also, things can change.
Paul: Always look into the API reference. So, for example, for TokenChunker, you can directly look into the implementation. So, this is a simple implementation that you can directly pick up. It has JavaScript support also.
Paul: Now, based on that implementation, what I have done, now, generally, I have taken a tokenized.
Paul: Okay, now, what type of tokenizer I have taken? The GPT-2 tokenizer. So, it has a BERT tokenizer as well as a GPT-2 tokenizer, and let's look into the API reference.
Paul: So, Character Tokenizer is the default one.
Paul: I'm just showing you the API reference documentation, because going forward, for every framework, please try to look into this.
Paul: So, a simple example. So, majorly, I feel that GPT is much better as compared to using only, the, I can say, the character tokenizer.
Paul: Now, in this implementation, really, the chunk size and the chunk overlap, okay, as you know that these are pretty much fixed indexes, this is the input.
Paul: And, like, this is your request, exactly, like, text, file, tokenizer, just chump size that you'll be passing.
Paul: Okay, and based on that, you will be getting the response, returns an array of chunk objects containing text, start index, end index, and token counts.
Paul: Okay, so please have a look into the API reference for every chunker I'm not going to show you. So, whenever you are doing the implementation, please look exactly what are the parameters that you have.
Paul: So, let's take here. I have taken the GPT one, I have not taken the character one. I feel that GPT is better as compared to the character. So, two things,
Paul: From, a chonky import tokenizer from tokenizer's import tokenizer. So, here, tokenizer.tokenize from pre-trained, the GPT version that I have picked up.
Paul: And this tokenizer directly, I am passing it, and here I have defined.
Paul: Okay, now here, fixed tools. So, when I'm talking about token chunker, the most general purpose, consistent size, high throughput applications, these things are mentioned, but really.
Paul: A fan of this one.
Paul: So, split text into fixed-sized token chunks, so it really doesn't understand what you have, it doesn't underst… try to understand in semantic meaning. It's a simple rule-based chunking.
Paul: Okay, so here, and the rules are defined based on the chunk size, okay, and the chunk overlap that you will decide.
Paul: Now, technical.txt, now this is the file that I am passing here. So, once the initialization of the chunker that we have done, based on that, I am, basically, I am using my helper functions. Two things. So, first of all, displaying the chunks and visually. So, these are my own custom functions that I have defined.
Paul: Okay, and let me execute them.
Paul: So, right here, based on the implementation, can you see here? I think you can see here the… let me show you the data.
Paul: I think Vita is there.
Paul: Beh.
Paul: And your sample technical doc.
Paul: This is the actual data that you have here.
Paul: So, chunky API documentation, overview, all right, installation. So, a few basic things are mentioned here. Now, really, it doesn't matter, what is mentioned.
Paul: It will directly follow the rule of 512, and nothing it will look into.
Paul: It really doesn't, matter whether it's a paragraph, whether, simply, like, it's a subparagraph, or any type of such structure.
Paul: Okay, and right now, you are getting the chunk.
Paul: Now, the token count that you are getting, okay, close to 512. Similarly, here I have done for every chunk.
Paul: You can click on the scroll level anyways. I have only taken 3 jumps. Guys, in the helper function, you can max this physical to 3. If you want, you can change this parameter to a higher number to look into more.
Paul: Now, when you look into this particular distribution, okay, so what are the things that you can understand? First of all time?
Paul: Because, directly, if I look into the statistics, the mean… okay, so here comes the frequency, here comes the token count. So, two distributions, the histogram and the box plot that I have taken. So, what are the inferences that I can take?
Paul: Let me…
Paul: Okay, so let's get this into the notes, okay? Because for every chunker, I have done a distribution and count. Okay, so let me just take this image for now, and I will paste it in my notepad, just wait.
Paul: Okay, so just wait, let's go back to the iPad.
Paul: Bachelor's correct.
Paul: Let's start my iPad… Okay, we…
Paul: Alright, so I got the image. Okay, let's try to decode this. So, first of all, the main purpose of this particular visualization, I can say.
Paul: Okay, is to look into each metric, like, what they are revealing. So, first of all, right here, if you look into the mean, so when you look into the mean, so what does mean represent here? Okay, so, first of all.
Paul: For me. Okay, so right now, the value that we are getting here is, 505.
Paul: In simple terms, so here I'm getting 505. So, what is the meaning of 505?
Paul: Meanings?
Paul: Average. So, from here, you can deduct, okay, the average chunk size.
Paul: And generally, like, my chunking, in my chunking, I have given that it should be 512.
Paul: Okay, so, yes, getting the result close to 505, I can say that, but the average is slightly below. Not very below, but I can say that it's below. Now, when you look into the mean, how it can be useful to you.
Paul: Just think.
Paul: Generally, when you look into the mean, how it will be useful.
Paul: When you are working, or you are actually deciding on your chunking strategy, and if you actually go with it, it doesn't matter on what type of chunker you are using. For every chunk, we'll be calculating the mean.
Paul: Generally, it is important, okay, like.
Paul: Always remember. Okay, storage I am writing, or memory requirements?
Paul: So, once you look into the mean, it actually gives you the idea. Whenever you are working with any third party, for example, Quadrant, I think in the cloud version, they give you 3G.
Paul: So from here, you can actually deduct, okay, so if I have 505 in average, okay, so based on that, how much memory that I can… so you can actually create your own helper function, and based on that, you can do the calculation.
Paul: Okay, so in that way, like, mean is always useful to me.
Paul: Then in the next step, you have median.
Paul: So, median is coming close to 512.
Paul: So, median is coming close to 512, I can say that. Okay. Now, what is the meaning of medium here?
Paul: The middle value, when the chunks are sorted by size, in simple terms, medium.
Paul: Yes, and when you look into Medium, Okay, so let's take medium.
Paul: with me.
Paul: So, what I can say from this insight, when I look into, okay, my medium is high.
Paul: So, most chunks are, near the max value.
Paul: Okay, and because when you look into, I can say that, yes, few outliers are there directly from block float, I can understand, yes, there are few small outliers, okay, which are basically pulling the average down, but this is good.
Paul: So I can say that if I look into my medium, I can decide that, yes, this is quite ideal, because most chunks are hitting our target size, but few outliers are there.
Paul: Yes, guys?
Paul: Please let me know.
Paul: Because when I look into that 512, and if I directly look… can I… I can directly decode that thing.
Paul: Most chunks are ideal, so I can say that, yes, it's idle.
Paul: Close to 512?
Paul: But… Few outliers are there.
Paul: Always remember that, so that's why, like, we calculate the mean-medium.
Paul: And then, in the next step, we have the standard deviation.
Paul: Which is coming close to 15.7.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: So, when you look into standard division 15.7, what does it tell us?
Paul: Simply standard deviation and simple statistics. What does it define? It measures the variability or the spread around the mean.
Paul: Okay, so in this case, I can say the standard deviation is very low.
Paul: Can I say yes or no?
Paul: Okay, so probably, like, 15… Okay, like…
Paul: You can simply take, like, if the mean is…
Paul: Coming 505, and based on that 15, I feel somewhere 30, close to… close to 3% it will come. 3% of the mean.
Paul: So, that's why. I think… close to 3, okay, so that's why.
Paul: Okay, now, when you are looking into a very low standard deviation, okay, what I can say, highly consistent.
Paul: Highly constant, consistent chunking that has taken place, and this is quite ideal.
Paul: Okay, so I will say that, yes, this is good.
Paul: So, highly consistent chunking that we have, but yes, in some cases, too, it has dropped.
Paul: Always remember for RAD, Okay, so for RAT, whenever you are working.
Paul: You should have low standard deviation.
Paul: It's good practice having a lower standard dev. It means that more predictable token, okay, per chunk, or basically the total number of tokens within a chunk, it becomes more predictable.
Paul: So that's why I feel that having a lower standard deviation is always good.
Paul: What is the high ST?
Paul: Generally, like, generally, when ISD will come, just think, the opposite of this.
Paul: Generally, like, the tokens within the chunk becomes very, very less predictable.
Paul: Okay, so generally for RAG solutions.
Paul: And in some cases, I have seen that higher standard deviation, like, within less use cases, we do use.
Paul: But, majorly, your standard deviation will be towards the lower side.
Paul: Always, remember that.
Paul: Okay, so lower the standard deviation, it's always better, I think.
Paul: Perfect. Now, in some cases, the standard deviation can be increased. It means that low standard dip, it doesn't mean that always it has to be very, very low. It can be high also, because if I always try to compare the mean with that.
Paul: Okay, so in this case, it was close to, like, 3% of the mean. Sometimes it can be 10% of the mean, sometimes 15%, 20%, but generally, most of the time, I can say less than 50% it will mean.
Paul: Yes, always take that stance.
Paul: Because based on your data, you have to calculate your own statistics, and from there, you can do the info.
Paul: Pollock.
Paul: Now, in the next step.
Paul: We have…
Paul: Our, mean and max, so mean and max, anybody can decode. What is the purpose of mean and max?
Paul: Mean and max defines your range.
Paul: I hope everybody understands mean and max. It's basically the range. There is nothing fancy here.
Paul: Mean, comma, max. It's a range definition.
Paul: So, here, it's coming 470,512.
Paul: 2512.
Paul: So, what is the token difference here? 42.
Paul: Now, pretty much narrow range, I can say. Okay, now this gives you much more.
Paul: So, like, if the difference is pretty much narrow, it tells you about an uniform
Paul: Chumps, I can say.
Paul: Pretty much uniform, like,
Paul: Because, you know, because of those outliers, for sure, few chunks will have listed tokens, and the range will be higher, but I can say for most chumps.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: Now, coming to the distribution. Okay, so in the next step, you have the distributions.
Paul: The first one is basically… Let's take…
Paul: Okay, so the… Left-hand side and the right-hand side. Which plot is this one?
Paul: Yes, guys, which plot?
Paul: Yeah, don't tell me, it's simple, say, histogram. I don't want to know right skewed or… okay? And, on the right-hand side, it's a box slot. Now, from this histogram, what you can understand, simply.
Paul: So, close to 470, this is somewhere around. The mean lies close to 505.
Paul: Okay, so here around 470 that we are getting.
Paul: Okay, so two main distinct groups that we have. So, one chunk is around 470, okay, and, basically, the…
Paul: other 5 chunks that I have. So, for 1 chunk, and for the other 5 chunks that I have, it's close to 510. Then that way, you can understand for each of your chunks.
Paul: Now, coming to the distribution, because really, from here, you cannot infer a lot of meaning, but let's try to understand this box plot. This box plot is important.
Paul: Deepak is asking, what is the basis of this chunking?
Paul: What is the basis? Deepak, your portion doesn't fit here. There is no basis. This is a simple token chunker that I have taken, and based on that, I'm showing you the stats. What is the basis? There is no basis.
Paul: If you really think about the parameters are, chunk overlap and chunk size, based on two things that you were doing.
Paul: Okay? Now, when you look into the box plot, what you can, take out, I can say that, yes, the outlier is there.
Paul: Around 700 and… 470 years on.
Paul: Okay, and I can say my box is very much compressed, around 512, which shows pretty much tight clustering. Yes, or…
Paul: Which confirms, basically, your low variance.
Paul: Okay, can I say that this is highly compressed, the mean box?
Paul: And which is around 512, because it's somewhere above this part, so I'm taking, like, 512 is my max number, based on that. This block spot actually confirms that you are having low variance.
Paul: Okay, so from, this simple stats, you can actually, take a lot of implications, like predictable cost, uniform retrieval, okay, then comes your token chunk count, those type of things you can always look into.
Paul: So, it's a good practice, and generally, like.
Paul: Nobody actually focuses on these things.
Paul: But when you'll be actually working in production, and when you'll be working with huge
Paul: data, then only you'll be working on stats. Otherwise, really, nobody works with stats. So I thought about keeping these chunks, because really, these statistics actually help you to gather a lot of information.
Paul: Later on, when your solution becomes bigger and bigger with respect to time, your data increases, this will actually make sense.
Paul: But if you're having small data, really, like, the sense will be towards the worst.
Paul: Hold it.
Paul: Okay, so majorly the things we have already gone through, and I hope everybody understood the stats.
Paul: Yes?
Paul: Yes or no? Because going forward, for every chunker, I've kept those stats. So, for a few people, it might be useful, but for a few, it might not be. So, not a while, so let's get back to our…
Paul: Not implementation, so desktop.
Paul: Who?
Paul: Yes, 10-20% overlap will be there, because you were telling. It can be more than 20% also.
Paul: When you have defined the chunk size, so here only you are taking that.
Paul: from the… Once you have defined.
Paul: I think… Generally, it's a good practice to keep your overlap between 10-20%. Sometimes 25% also, I've seen.
Paul: That's the rear.
Paul: I think, the implementations that we have done, it's working for everybody. Please let me know.
Paul: For the first one that you have taken.
Paul: Okay, now, here, simply, like, try out and experiment with the parameters, the chunk size and the chunk overlap. Okay, as I have told, that these are hyperparameters that need to be decided by you. Nobody knows what is the perfect number. Analyze your data, try to do experiments.
Paul: Okay, and if you remember in the last class, we already have Looked into this.
Paul: Anybody remembers in the last class, when you guys did that, when I shared the notebook, you guys solved and did it by yourself, you fixed the code?
Paul: Nobody remembers.
Paul: It really does.
Paul: If you are not there, nothing I can do, but I think in the… Somewhere around that time.
Paul: Go through that, notebook, I think.
Paul: Evaluating the ideal chunk size.
Paul: If people have missed the class, please at least go through the class. I think they're…
Paul: You have this Lama Index tutorial. In this Lama Index tutorial, you have this particular notebook.
Paul: Because I remember most of you did it in the class only, I shared the solution. So, this one. Please go through this.
Paul: Okay, and try to use an open source, because here…
Paul: People have spent in the last class close to $1.
Paul: Okay, alright, now let's get back.
Paul: Now, coming to sentence chunkers. Okay, now, sentence boundary preservation.
Paul: Okay, so let's into the, looks into the docs.
Paul: Client-side exception, sometimes that happens here. Okay, alright.
Paul: So here, the second one that we have is your sentence chunker.
Paul: So, sentence, I hope everybody understands. Sentence. So, simply split, text based on the chain.
Paul: Chunks while preserving complete sentences, ensuring that each chunk maintains proper sentence boundaries.
Paul: and context. Really, like, sentence chunkering, not a fan of this one, doesn't make a lot of sense, but here you are passing the minimum sentences per chunk.
Paul: Okay, so really, like, this is a hyperparameter.
Paul: Now, on top of the research paper text that I have, I'm applying this.
Paul: Now, if you really look into the syntax, if you really try to compare it with the Langshan text letters, it's simple, it's just two lines.
Paul: Okay, the import and the core implementation. Once you have done the initialization, the rest is basically passing your data. So here, I'm passing my data, which is basically a research paper text that we have.
Paul: And here, I've taken the minimum sentences per chunk.
Paul: Okay, and let me execute this. So, here, two sentences that I have taken.
Paul: So, based on that, so, retrieval…
Paul: token chunker, abstract. Now, if you really look into
Paul: This is for my initial…
Paul: First of all, this is the token chunks one, and then you have the second one. Okay, so always look into, this is the token chunker, first chunk, and this is the sentence chunker.
Paul: So when you look here, can I say that in this case, it's pretty much the same?
Paul: But at this point, because I'm printing only 300, let's try to increase it to,
Paul: a bigger value. Let's take 600 for now. I hope 600 characters are there.
Paul: So, here, based on that… because right now, it's simply based on boundaries, but I can say that it's closed only.
Paul: Because right now, based on the data that I have provided, okay, and if you try to change the number of sentences here, that also you can do.
Paul: So, let's pick up… Read this time.
Paul: So, based on that, okay, the abstract, okay, chunk 1 abstract, the token count is coming close to 472. 489…
Paul: 479.
Paul: Alright… And let's try to look into the distribution, and let's try to analyze from here.
Paul: So, when you look into the V,
Paul: So directly, just try to focus here on what are the things that you can reduce.
Paul: If you directly compare into the plots, let me know, because if you directly look into the text, I can see that, yes, here the token count is coming close to 472, 489, 479, or somewhere close to 500. I will say this is a good start, at least.
Paul: And based on the recent
Paul: Text that we have. Okay, and let's try to look into the data also, it's important.
Paul: This is the actual data that you have.
Paul: Okay, so based on semantic chunking, abstract.
Paul: Okay. Now, really, like, when you look into sentences, do you think that this is a sentence?
Paul: This is a sentence.
Paul: So, how many of you think that in your data there will always be sentences?
Paul: it's not necessary, your data will have sentences, really, like, it's not real, like, so I'm not a fan of this one, but, really, if you look into, okay, it has covered this part, so…
Paul: Based on that, if you try to analyze.
Paul: Chunk 1 now. I will just change this to… 1 and let's C.
Paul: This time, I'm gone with a lower one.
Paul: Alright, abstract.
Paul: Okay, the first syntax, the neural approaches.
Paul: Chunk 2, based on that. And most of the times, I'm getting somewhere close to
Paul: 512, because the sentence chunker is trying to retain the chunk size, but at least, the mean cause. Because, see, here.
Paul: The size that you are trying to maintain.
Paul: is 512 per chunk, but it will try to maintain based on sentence logic, so wherever it will find the sentence, based on that. But right now, I can see that it's 472. So, let's look into the plot. So, from here, can I say that there is one outlier.
Paul: And I simply deduct yes or no.
Paul: And what is the mean here? The mean is coming 471.
Paul: So if you try to compare, the mean with the median.
Paul: The same logic like, just like last time.
Paul: Whether it lies or not.
Paul: Last time, Please check, guys, and then tell me.
Paul: medium and the mean. What is the difference? Last time, I think the difference was towards the lower side. It was 512 with 505 or 6, I don't remember, but it was clear.
Paul: Last time it was 515.
Paul: Yes, Outlier is there, but till now, I can say that, first of all, just look into the histogram and try to understand, because based on the multiple chunks, for the first chunk, this is close to 400. For the second one, starting from here again.
Paul: This is close to 480. And finally, I can say the last chunk that you have, this was around, close to 500.
Paul: Well, this is somewhere in between, so 490 that you can take for now, or close to 480.
Paul: So, right now, if you look into the mean and the median.
Paul: I can say that most chunks are, again, like, near, but this time less near, because the target was 512. But when you're working with sentence chunker, you know that.
Paul: It really, like, when you were looking into a sentence, so for sure, if a sentence gets missed at 512 mark, you will be fine. In less number of times, you will…
Paul: And I try to reach somewhere close to 500 also. So here, I can say that most of the averages are coming which is between this one, because close to 3 appearance of 480 to 490. This is much more focused on this side.
Paul: So, I can say that,
Paul: I cannot say most of the chunks are hitting my ideal size that we have decided of 512, but as compared to our previous one, we are having less infants.
Paul: So here, if you look, the standard deviation is higher as compared to last time, for sure.
Paul: Because, this time, how much of the mean it will come. So, probably, previously, it was close to 3%. This time, it will come… how much? Like, 13 to 10, 300, try to take.
Paul: Somewhere around.
Paul: Around 15, I can say.
Paul: That 3% has increased to 15, but this is also acceptable. In most of the cases of center chunkers, the standard deviation will be higher. So, close to around 15, that, roughly, that I'm taking here.
Paul: Now, mean and max value. Focus on this one, the mean and the max. This is really important.
Paul: Now, this can happen. There can be a sentence which is very, very long.
Paul: Yes or no?
Paul: Because max value is close to 498, this is close to 512, I know this value is fine. But why this value is dropping up 394, which is the minimum?
Paul: There can be a sentence which came, and it was crossing the mark of 512, probably, like, 540. Because of that big sentence, it has dropped. Yes or no.
Paul: So here, the mean justifies itself.
Paul: Because it totally depends upon the data.
Paul: Generally, if it was a long title, it… see, generally, I'm talking about sentences, so titles are also tilted as sentences.
Paul: Okay, it will… it won't understand the structure, like, header 1, header 2, header 3, like, in markdown files you have. It doesn't matter to it.
Paul: All right.
Paul: So, I can say here, really, when I look into this one, so I can say that this is not compressed.
Paul: Okay, so this is…
Paul: Pretty much the opposite form, but I can say majorly the chance lies between 400 and…
Paul: Like, 70… okay, I'm below that 500 mark.
Paul: So, somewhere close to 500, it was trying to target, but it's not really it. So, like, set, really, like, sentence…
Paul: chunkers don't like to use it a lot. Again, not a fan of that.
Paul: And this is a simple output comparison, if you're really looking. Now, coming to the lan chain, now this recursive chunker, hierarchical splitting.
Paul: What are the conditions of this one?
Paul: Recursive chunker.
Paul: What is the first thing? Slash slash N. Then comes slash n.
Paul: Then comes dot.
Paul: Then comes space. How many of you remember chat logic, previously, that we have discussed in the Langchen class?
Paul: Because the same thing happens here also.
Paul: Okay, so here it's simply a recursive chunker that they call, which is basically the hierarchical setting. What is the hierarchy?
Paul: Always remember that, that hierarchy doesn't change. Double slash n, single slash n, dot, okay, and then finally, if nothing happens, it's based on characters. Okay, so yes, paragraph, line, sentence. So, double slash n means paragraph, always remember that.
Paul: Alright, now, recursive character splitter, as I told you, more than 60-70% of the times, recursive character splitter works.
Paul: Now, it's really good, okay, for markdown documents, I feel that this is really good. And from the implementation, again, so let's pick something from here.
Paul: You have already defined the tokenizer, again, which is based on GPT-2. Chunk size, again, close to 512 that we are targeting. So, let's look.
Paul: Here, the… how the stats feels like.
Paul: Alright, now, when I look into this one.
Paul: Okay, for my initial changa, I can say that
Paul: This is towards the lower side, having 360.
Paul: Somewhere around.
Paul: Okay, one drop in the stats, but can I say that,
Paul: This is somehow better, at least, if you look into this graph also.
Paul: Because if you really look into the mean, 478.
Paul: And now, this mean can change, because there are hierarchies that have been defined.
Paul: hierarchies when I'm talking. So, first of all, it will try to look for paragraphs. If there are no paragraphs, then it will try to look for, basically sentences, okay?
Paul: or a single line, if I say the slash n parameter that comes, then that way it will try to look. So, in our case, the data that we have provided, so directly I can say that, yes, this looks good, but at the end of the day, there is an outlier, just because of this 360 that is coming, which is pretty much far away.
Paul: And it's, pulling down your meme.
Paul: standard tape, I can say. Now, if you really look into the numbers here.
Paul: the mean and the medium. What is the inference that you can take? Can I say a very similar inference, but this time the standard deviation has increased
Paul: Yes, so less than 10%,
Paul: But, yes, because the standard deviation is right now close to 10%, I can… Not lesser than 10%.
Paul: Because if I make it 10, it becomes 580, so… Lesser than 10.
Paul: But, most of the times, you will see the standard deviation will always be low. It won't be very, very high.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: Now, if you really look into the minimum here, the 361 and 511. Now, from here, what you can deduce? Previously, this number that you had, okay, so first time, the max range is, like, close to 512, I can say this is good, but the mean has really dropped.
Paul: And from the standard deviation, simply, I can say that, yes, it's pretty much a
Paul: compressed, not very compressed as compared to our previous chunker, but I can say that this chunky is at least working better as previous to our sentence chunker. As simple as that. Because our main target was close to 512, and that particular boundary, we are trying to reach towards that.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: But, only that the mean and the max range difference is quite high, really. The token difference, if you really look into 511,360, so 111 plus.
Paul: 13a.
Paul: So that number, which is coming so close to
Paul: I think, 150 it will come. Yes? What is the token difference here? I think it will be close to 150.
Paul: Pretty much. So, this token difference is high, okay, and the token difference can come.
Paul: Okay, because, simply, you have to understand the rules, and these are all rule-based chunkers. Nothing LLM, nothing. So, whatever the rules that have been applied based on that, you will…
Paul: UDEC.
Paul: Yes, everywhere there is a recursive chunker. Recursive is the world's most used chunking strategy.
Paul: So, every library will have a recursive version of it.
Paul: Alright, now this plot looks, good to me. Okay, later on, printing some information.
Paul: Now, I will come to some specialized chunkers. Okay, so before moving into the specialized chunkers, so here, let's look into the documentation also. So, decursive level rules that have been applied here.
Paul: I mean… initialization from the recipes. Now, generally here, you have an added benefit.
Paul: Now, recursive chunker now on what type of file that you want to apply, so this support is also available. So, I feel that we are working with English, but you can decide, like here, basically on Markdown. So you don't need a separate markdown splitter. In Lanshan, if you remember, there was a separate splitter markdown.
Paul: How many of you remember that?
Paul: Markdown, splitters, inline chain.
Paul: Now, the same implementation directly through here, like, what type of file can actually pass it?
Paul: Now, if you, really look into, the params here, okay.
Paul: Now, right here, based on the initialization, so your custom rules, that also you can define.
Paul: And let's look into the API reference for this. The API reference is useful here.
Paul: Okay, now, what type of recipe that you want to pass? So, majorly, like, markdown files, if you are working with, otherwise, if it is text, then you don't need to pass the recipe. So, the specific file definition, that particular option is also there.
Paul: And from here, you can look the file type, text, file, whichever is required.
Paul: And having face repo, and the default language is strict to English only. Right now, the multilingual support is coming. Till now, I feel that a lot of support is missing, but right now, we are discussing majorly with English, but I know in future, the support for a few other languages will also come.
Paul: Because right now, they are working with Mandarin, French, Uri, and a few other languages. It's in development state.
Paul: Now, let's…
Paul: look into our next level. Now, from here, we'll be talking about some specialized chunkers. Now, very specifically, table or CSV files. A very similar implementation was also available in Langchen.
Paul: Where you had CSV-based chunkers, okay? So, generally, like, good for markdown tables. So, what type of document that I have taken here? So, sample table. Can you see here?
Paul: These are simple markdown tables for me.
Paul: SampleTable.md, and these are all tables that I have kept.
Paul: Not in every chunker, you'll be getting the parameter of chunk overlap so much.
Paul: That's the thing. Every time you won't be getting.
Paul: It depends upon what type of chunker, there only you can pass.
Paul: Now, really, like, these things that I'm discussing, it totally comes with experiments.
Paul: Okay, now, table chunkos…
Paul: are, good whenever you are working with CSV, XLS-based files, those type of support that you have.
Paul: And majorly, the chunk size that I'm hitting around is 5112. There, I have passed that input, sample table 5. Okay, and right now, just try to look into the chunks.
Paul: So right now, the split has been based on 5 chunks on the top of the table chunker.
Paul: Yeah, and if you really look into it, Based on our headers.
Paul: Okay, so… let's try to analyze.
Paul: Now, when you look here.
Paul: I can see that, okay, the core 512 dat hit mark is actually including 2 doubles.
Paul: Because it's not necessary that a single table is only coming.
Paul: Can I say that it has actually taken two levels. Now, if you look into feature comparison with language agnostic, okay, now this is the part. Now, here, if you really look into…
Paul: feature comparison.
Paul: With language agnostic.
Paul: Now, exactly what is the data, because the performance metrics across different, okay, now this data can try to analyze the data.
Paul: Okay, overlap support.
Paul: Because overlap support is here, here, fine.
Paul: Then this is the fourth one.
Paul: Fourth one is language agnostic, okay? So, here we can see… now, can I say that somehow, like, a part of the table has been broken, okay, and it has been kept in the other chunk? Yes or no?
Paul: Y es bundo.
Paul: Like, again, if I change this, and let's make it 1.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: Okay, so share based on that, table chunk information.
Paul: getting,
Paul: Because right now, I have just changed the index. Because total 5 chunks have been there, and I'm looking into the second one. So, here, it has started from…
Paul: the resource, alright? Now, if you really look into somewhere, the idea is that whether it's preserving the complete table or not. But here, complete table preservation is really not taking place.
Paul: Because it's simply rule-based, so for sure, it's breaking the table. And generally, working with tables is basically working with, other paths, like some type of OCR-based mechanisms is always better in this case.
Paul: performance metrics, LLM power, resource requirement with Newell Chunker. I feel that till this point, it has skipped the entire…
Paul: Okay, yes, at every point of time, whenever the table is there, the header that we have defined, this is a markdown file, so it's trying to capture. And very specifically, it's not a header, if you really think about this as part of the table.
Paul: The core header information that you have within our actual data.
Paul: Alright.
Paul: Yes, it can work with every, like, you can test it, PPT docs, every type of support is…
Paul: You have to just pass the file, so that way they don't mention what are the different type of file types and others.
Paul: No, really, like, I feel that somehow the table information is not completely preserved every time.
Paul: Let me just open.
Paul: Splits large Markdown tables into small, manageable chunks, especially API-based.
Paul: Uses a recursive endpoint to access table chunking functionality, because behind the scenes, it's huge.
Paul: Now, let's come into Code Chunker, okay? Now, Code Chunker uses ASTs. How many of you know about abstract syntax trees?
Paul: Because this is the logic everywhere, whether it's in LangChain, Lama Index, if you're working with Python files.
Paul: If you're working with JavaScript files.
Paul: Yes, please let me know.
Paul: Using abstract trees, anybody… any idea?
Paul: Because what does, actually, abstract twist does? ASTs.
Paul: Abstract syntax strings, what they do.
Paul: So, let's talk a little bit about abstract syntax trees.
Paul: I have worked on this one a lot, so let's talk about it.
Paul: break code into symbols. It's not only about symbols.
Paul: Just wait, let me open my chart, I put my table…
Paul: Money.
Paul: So, first of all, when I'm talking with respect to abstract syntax trees.
Paul: Now, apps are syntax is generally where you learn this particular concept.
Paul: Dead, guys.
Paul: Where you have learned this concept.
Paul: Anyone?
Paul: Nobody has learned doing any of this.
Paul: All right, fine. If you have not learned, okay, forget about that. Right now, I'll be talking about rules, because there also you have rule-based information.
Paul: Okay, so for, first of all, when I'm talking about these abstracts and text trees, okay, so generally the chunking will happen based on some logic. Okay, now, generally, the logic can be different. So, AHDB's chunking, okay, it preserves the first thing, like, it will try to look for functions.
Paul: Okay, it will try to look for classes.
Paul: Any other things, then probably it can look for methods.
Paul: It can look for import sections also.
Paul: Okay, and probably, like, some type of control logic that you have defined, so I can write here, some type of control blocks.
Paul: Based on these type of logics, it tries, okay?
Paul: To, preserve the semantic boundaries. So this is the AST-based chunking that happens. Whereas in traditional text chunking, it can break your piece of code anywhere.
Paul: Okay, so it simply loses the scope.
Paul: Now, whenever, you are applying a code chunker, so what happens in high level? So, let's talk about the high-level overview.
Paul: So you are passing some type of source code file.
Paul: Okay? You have your main source code with you. Now, on top of the next source code, you'll be having a AST parser.
Paul: Okay, now this AST parser has to be language-specific. It's very, very important.
Paul: Every language has its own AST password. It has to be language-specific always.
Paul: Generally, when you work with,
Paul: problem statement where we are working with documentation, generating code. In those cases, ASTs will be working in detail much more. Now, from these AST parser, the output of the parser becomes multiple node that comes, because these are trees.
Paul: Okay, at the end of the day, these trees will be having your nodes.
Paul: Now, what are these nodes?
Paul: These notes are basically functions, classes, whatever that you can think for now. I've written so many things, I will write only two things.
Paul: Once these nodes are available, then comes your chunking part. Chunk your boundaries.
Paul: Okay? Like, boundaries that are chosen at node level, simply.
Paul: Now, once the chunkies are done, most of the times, I can say, you will be getting semantically complete code chunks.
Paul: I have worked on this one a lot.
Paul: on coding patterns and these things. So, generally, it's like AST trees are really good, and you'll be working with a lot of AST passes, and you actually work with more than 30 programming languages.
Paul: Okay, so generally, when you are working with building some type of code assistant and those things, that, code chunkers are really helpful.
Paul: I hope everybody got the core idea.
Paul: Yes?
Paul: And generally, if you ask me how the AST knows, okay, so most of the AST node, from your tree, when it will be broken into node, it always knows what is the start line, nest line, or any type of nested children that might come.
Paul: Okay, so simply it understands. So, previously, it knows, like, what are the mean logic, or basically the indentation patterns, how a particular programming language works. Okay, and how are the syntaxes? So that's why it is always language-specific, always remember that.
Paul: Alright, now let's get back to our implementation.
Paul: It will take time, I will complete this entire chunky.
Paul: Next, so… green.
Paul: Kiran is asking, Dockling and Chunky are names associated with software libraries for…
Paul: you can docklink and chonky. How many of you think Docklink and Chonky are pretty much the same stuff?
Paul: Please let me know.
Paul: Please let me know, guys, how many of you think Dockling and Chunky are same?
Paul: So, see, in Doppling, okay, you will be reading a file.
Paul: Only that part.
Paul: Once the file is read, you have the data.
Paul: Now, on top of the data, you'll be applying chonky. So, both are different things.
Paul: Okay, so don't ask that question, because data parsing is different, a different component, and chunking is a different component.
Paul: Yes, chunk is pretty much, like, downstream task.
Paul: Alright, now let's just wait. Let's get in the reboot.
Paul: And, generally, here you have batch-level features also for any type of junker. So right now, port chunker that I have given, so that language-specific definition, language is equal to Python. For now, I've taken a simple source code file.
Paul: Okay, and the chunk size. So, generally, the chunk size in programming language, it's a good practice to keep it, like, close to 2,000. Even 3,000. Now, this is just an exception.
Paul: If you are working with text data, okay, like, if you try to compare, like, code files or also text data, but when you are working very specifically with source code files.
Paul: It's a good practice to keep higher chun size. Don't keep a small chunk size, because probably, if within a class, okay, if the length of the class is very, very long, you are having a lot of functions within that, okay, it becomes a problem.
Paul: to always go with a higher chunk side. This is the only exception case in your entire chunking strategy.
Paul: only this is the major one. In other places, it's good, you can work with 512 tools.
Paul: But when you are working with actual source code files, okay, always try to go with a higher number. This number can be higher also, 3000 also. It totally depends upon, like, the code size when you will look into.
Paul: Because if you are going with smaller size, and if your code breaks, simply the logic breaks, it doesn't matter only. Because the semantic meaning of that code will be lost.
Paul: Alright, so let me get that. So here, I think I have passed.
Paul: Put text file.
Paul: This is samplecode.py file, directly, as you can see, so this is the file that I have taken here.
Paul: Alright, now…
Paul: Now, here, if you want AST-level, information, so this particular feature is not available in Langchen or others, but if you really want to look into the AST nood information, that is also possible in chunky.
Paul: Now, chunk is much more, if you want to do much more depth and much more research, just on chunky, and really, really less…
Paul: For them does it.
Paul: Now, we will come to our main one, which is that semantic or embedding-based chunkers formula.
Paul: Because these chunkers are, like, embedding to identify some type of semantic boundaries.
Paul: Now, from here, semantic chunking, guys. In the last class, I think last to last class, somewhere, I've given you a high-level overview.
Paul: Semantic chunker is available in every framework, okay, because after recursive character text better, the concept comes off semantic chunker.
Paul: Now, this is where your topic boundary detection happens, and what we'll be using here some typo.
Paul: LLM. It means that some type of embedding model that you'll be using.
Paul: Inhibitor remembers in previous classes that I have taken, so let's get back to moods.
Paul: Do you have to add a magical library? No.
Paul: Just wait, let's get back to our moods here.
Paul: I think in the last class, I have discussed this a bit.
Paul: Somehow, I don't…
Paul: Alright, yes.
Paul: Okay, so semantic chunking, when I, told you about this particular, one, okay? So, generally, what happens in semantic chunk?
Paul: like, and it is generally good when you have multi-topic documents, okay, different type of documents, like, within a single document, you have a lot of information, and they can be totally or completely different. In those cases, really, it is helpful.
Paul: So, you will be having your main doc. From those, you will be taking sentences, and then, finally, you will be doing the embedding feature.
Paul: Based on that, a simple… these are the sentences. This is a simple paragraph, based… break that paragraph into multiple sentences, and finally, you do that, okay? And then finally, you will be calculating the embedding for each sentence, and then you'll be performing a grouping operation.
Paul: Grouping of those sentences in a single chart.
Paul: Ideally, within a chunk, if you're having the sentences, they should be having very similar, similarity. Okay, it means that the similarity should not be very, very far.
Paul: Okay, now, let's try to look into a custom implementation, because I feel that this is important somewhere.
Paul: So, I will just stop sharing, and let's get back to our notes.
Paul: Well, this is desktop 3.
Paul: Perfect.
Paul: So, here, for our semantic chumper, chumper, so uses embeddings to find topic boundaries, and based on semantic similarity. So, excellent semantic coherence, natural topic boundaries, auto-threshold detection. So, how does, auto-threshold detection when I'm talking? So, generally, like, what is the threshold that you should keep?
Paul: For your semantic similarity, what is a good threshold that you fill that in?
Paul: Should keep it.
Paul: Because I don't work with auto, I try to keep with higher numbers always. Always try to keep with more than 75. 05 is the very least.
Paul: Amount. Okay, don't use… always try to stick more than 80% at least.
Paul: Okay? There is… temperature is a different concept, not too sure.
Paul: Now, first of all here, I'm using the OpenAI embedding, so I've just switched to OpenAI.
Paul: Now, if you really look into the semantic chunk, okay, the embedding, so first of all, for our
Paul: Semantic chunker, you need an embedding model.
Paul: So here I have passed, I am using the OpenAI embeddings.
Paul: Okay, threshold. So, this threshold, previously, they were actually working with automatically email that, by default, they have set, but this time, manually, I passed it, threshold is equal to 0.8.
Paul: The chunk size, again, I have decided which is close to 512, and the minimum number of sentences, that is 1. You can pass two sentences also.
Paul: Three sentences off.
Paul: No restriction on that. So, generally, I prefer to use 1, 2, 3, I don't go more than that.
Paul: Now, here, so, now this is a paid operation. It means that I'm making a call to OpenAI. You can use Gemini, there is no issue.
Paul: Now here I am passing. It means that the document that I'll be passing, this research paper text, okay, now this document will be broken into sentences. Once the sentences are done, then
Paul: what will happen in the next step? Embedding. Once the embedding is done, then actually you'll be doing the grouping of those sentences into multiple chunks. Now, in this particular process, because here, directly it is applied.
Paul: that now… might think I have not defined my OpenAI embeddings.
Paul: I think it's true to MOC.
Paul: Okay, now, really, this will take a long time, and here you will see the distribution. It is really important to look into this distribution, because this will vary.
Paul: So, when you look into the distribution here.
Paul: What is the mean value?
Paul: for this.
Paul: What is the mean value guys?
Paul: Can you see a very, very huge shift?
Paul: Yes, I'm… This is actually a very huge shift.
Paul: Whatever the things that we have learned till now, this is the, like, biggest shift that we're looking into.
Paul: Generally, for, code level, see, if you are working with code, I have not done the distribution. They are very specifically for code junkers. So, really, for code level, this statistic doesn't matter to us, because code has a very unique, thing that you cannot express it directly.
Paul: Because you know that. Somebody might write a function in two lines, somebody might do it in one line, but really, that doesn't matter. But here, this information is actual, because this is an actual piece of text, right? It's not code.
Paul: Can I say that the mean has dropped to 56?
Paul: This is a massive change.
Paul: what is the median value now? 40? So, really, like, when you look into how many of you feel that, on top of the data that we are using, we should apply semantic charging.
Paul: Just think and decide.
Paul: Many of you think that semantic chunking really works very, very good, but it's not always that.
Paul: Where your other chunker fails, then only you will have to move to semantic, because it always comes with a cost.
Paul: So if you re… So I can say that the mean has dropped to close to 55.
Paul: Okay, and right now, based on the settings, my target is 512.
Paul: Chunk.
Paul: But majorly, based on the distribution that I have.
Paul: Alright, now, if you really look into the chart here, semantic, now, this is the first one. Only. Okay, now, semantics and strategies, this is the first part.
Paul: Of the document.
Paul: I think this is the document. Can you see? Now this is one.
Paul: This is one channel.
Paul: Okay, now let's move to abstract part.
Paul: So here… again, here I can see that…
Paul: Really, like, again, dot dot dot, it means that it's continued with a bigger chunk.
Paul: Then comes central to RAG again here, not the token count is… really value.
Paul: Initially, the token count was close to 270, because here, a few information of this one that I had. Then, in the next level, this has really dropped.
Paul: Okay, 262. Now, let me change this number of sentences to 3, because you will see the… because you have to do the experiment in one shot, getting the perfect one.
Paul: It's hard, because really, like, having only 50 characters or 60 characters in a churn is a problematic thing.
Paul: Now, initially, if I look into…
Paul: The total number of chunks, and here again, based on 62, not a lot has changed.
Paul: And now, chunk 3, if you really look into it, the token count is 19.
Paul: And my target was 512.
Paul: So, really a big, big drop, I can say.
Paul: Okay, I'm majorly, if you look into the box plot here. Now, can I say that the outlier has changed?
Paul: Yes or no?
Paul: The outlier has changed.
Paul: In one case, somehow it has reached more than 200.
Paul: Okay, and rest of the times, usually the distribution lies.
Paul: somewhere around, I can say, like, medially varied. What is the mean range that is coming? Here, the mean is radiated, so the token difference that you have, and the highest one is 217.
Paul: So, which is basically the outlier, that simply says here, the standard deviation, though it has increased, but really, not a fruitful meaning, I can say, from here that I can get. So, like, semantic chunker, it works really good, but again, you have to decide on what type of data.
Paul: Okay, and for this particular document that I had, because directly I've applied on top of this document, and for this document, really, like, 49 chunks.
Paul: I don't feel that practically 49 chunks are required.
Paul: Again, again, based on the implementation.
Paul: So, I can say that semantic chunking is good, but when every other chunker will fail for him.
Paul: Then only go ahead with semantic chunk.
Paul: Okay, now the question comes a little bit about a custom implementation, because from here, yeah, really, you really don't know.
Paul: how everything is happening, because everything is behind the scenes. So let's take a custom implementation.
Paul: I have to keep that custom implementation here.
Paul: Okay, and anybody who's interested, okay, you can have a look into this one.
Paul: Little bit, I'll be talking about this custom implementation.
Paul: Okay, and just wait, I will share this notebook with you guys.
Paul: And generally, in Langchain, in Llama Index, everywhere this is available.
Paul: Again, like, not always good.
Paul: Now, see, I have taken cosine similarity, cosine distances, and few auto-tokenizers. Now, this is pretty much a scratch implementation. It means that whatever the text that will be passed, it will be broken into sentences. Okay, then comes the combining the sentences. Okay, now…
Paul: Again, these are all functions that I have defined. Now, I have two separate functions calculating the cosine distances, where I'll be passing the embeddings. Okay, and then comes your gate embeddings. Here, I have passed a very specific model.
Paul: This is an embedding model which is directly available in Arlingface. You can use it for free, and it's really a good one.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: Now, here comes the concept of mean pool that I have applied. So, really, I'll be coming to this concept of mean pooling, it's really important in semantic
Paul: And, how, like, it impacts your result.
Paul: Okay, so simple utility functions, one for splitting, then one for combining. Okay, then one function I have for calculating the cosine distances.
Paul: One to get the embeddings. Okay, and finally, one I have for mean pooling. Now, this is a mean pooling operation. There are multiple types of pooling, but for now, just focus on mean pool, which is widely used in RAC, or document retrieval type of task.
Paul: Now, this is a function in this particular function. I'll be passing some amount of text, and based on that, I'll be getting some information. Now, if you really look into this piece of text that I have passed here, is it so simply…
Paul: Now… Let's try to apply first chunk. Text, I think I have not defined chunk.
Paul: Alright, let me just run all.
Paul: Now, this is an embedding similarity-based chunking, okay, which is, like, one type
Paul: Or basically, your semantic chunking strategy.
Paul: Now, in this particular chunking strategy, first I have applied with splitting the sentences.
Paul: Then comes combining the sentences where I am using simple.
Paul: And you can use a simple join operation also.
Paul: There's, functions to calculate your cosine distances.
Paul: function to calculate, to get your emittings, and finally, depthChunkText. Okay, now this is the actual function that I'll be calling. In this particular function, you can see, first, I'm calling my split sentences.
Paul: Okay? So first, the splitting operation that we are doing.
Paul: Now, in the next step, after splitting, print, single sentences list, so one by one you can print. Then comes combining the sentences, the next one. Now, once the sentences are available, get embeddings. Now, gate embeddings, I'm calling from where, actually, your embeddings
Paul: will be created.
Paul: And finally, I am calculating the cosine distance. Okay, and then I told you, you have to pick up a threshold, and right now, the threshold that I am using is 80%, so this is a breakpoint percent type threshold, and using numbai.
Paul: Okay, I have defined, and right now, if you look into the analysis, where the distance exceeds the calculated threshold.
Paul: First of all, from this point, you'll be getting, or you are calculating.
Paul: For each point, what are the distances? And right now, if it doesn't satisfy that particular condition.
Paul: then it will be kept in chunks. So, for every chunks, I have created a blank list, because here I'll be appending the sentences one by one. So, through a for loop that I have taken that into account.
Paul: Now, in this particular implementation, so first of all, if you really look into, the actual text data, so regular exercises done, okay, now, if you really look into the chunks, now, these are all information related to the embedding model, so not really useful to you, but focus on this part. Chunk 1.
Paul: In the chunk 1,
Paul: I can say that, yes, I have more number of sentences, chunk 2. Somehow, I can say lesser number of sentences as compared to chunk 1 and chunk 3. So…
Paul: this point.
Paul: Let's try to look into the starting point and the ending point of our core jump. The regular exercise is essential.
Paul: Okay, and regular workout, so this is the part where enhanced mobility.
Paul: If you really look into NAS mobile, it is, I can say, really, the first chunk has taken this.
Paul: I should look into the second one.
Paul: Moreover, exercise contributes to better sleep and improved mood, which are crucial for daily functioning, and somehow…
Paul: If you look, it's talking about some exercises, walking, jogging… okay, till everyone, till this part, I can say.
Paul: Somehow, till this part.
Paul: This is your Chunk 2 that you have.
Paul: Now, chunk 3 by setting, realistic goals. Now, this is the end part, so for sure, whatever will be remaining. But if you really look into this, particular entire piece of text, try to analyze that. In the first chunk, so that I am talking about exercises.
Paul: Okay, in the second chunk, also, I'm talking about exercises. In the third chunk.
Paul: Really not about exercises. Now, this is the one where I feel that less exercises that we are talking about
Paul: So, fine, I can understand that somehow the similarity will be toward the lower side. Okay, for this sentences, so that's why it has been kept separately.
Paul: But this one, when I look into it.
Paul: Like, moreover, exercises contribute. Again, here, exercises.
Paul: Help in controlling the weight, okay? Improving cardiovascular, okay, alright.
Paul: Here again… because, really, like, if you try to really understand directly by looking into the text, it is not possible for me.
Paul: How many of you think that by looking into the text way, you can gather the information?
Paul: Please let me know. Do you think that you can understand?
Paul: Because the embeddings are created, but really how they are being done.
Paul: Because, I cannot understand it. I sometimes, like, if I was there, I will say that, okay, try to group all these sentences in one place.
Paul: Okay, probability till this point, because till this point, I feel that
Paul: Most of the sentences are talking about workouts, okay, or some exercises, which have very similar meaning in the high-dimensional embedding space, that I can say. Somewhere in the last part, I feel that, again, a little bit less focused towards
Paul: The exercises part.
Paul: Oh, really, like,
Paul: When you actually look into the core implementation, because here there is always a risk.
Paul: Okay, of not always getting the correct information.
Paul: Because in semantic chunking, the major problem is, are you using a good embedding model?
Paul: Because I have used something Like this one.
Paul: Which is a free version. And really, the one that I have done it, and based on that, the output that I'm looking into.
Paul: I feel that…
Paul: It can be better, because really the requirement of chunk 2 is not required, because here I have not passed any chunk size, guys. Okay, so directly. So, it can fit it, so there is no certain restriction that I have passed. If you're really looking to, I have not passed any chunk size here.
Paul: Okay, it means that it can do the grouping in any way.
Paul: There is no limitation. But somehow I feel that, based on the results that I had.
Paul: Really, it's not so much… Good.
Paul: Now, it is in my use case, but again, it totally depends. If I change the amount of data, probably I might get better results at any point of time.
Paul: Okay, so the analyze of the data, because here, I feel that somehow, the result doesn't satisfy.
Paul: Now, when should you use semantic chunking? Can anybody tell me?
Paul: When you should use semantic chunking.
Paul: Because this is a custom implementation that I have shown, but really, like, how many of you feel that semantic chunker is helpful? When?
Paul: Because this was an idea.
Paul: This idea came from just, Twitter.
Paul: tweet. Okay, because this chunking strategy actually came from a Twitter tweet.
Paul: Somebody posted in Twitter, and based on that, somebody has done the implementation. In some cases, it really works good, but I feel that in…
Paul: in use cases where you have very large, complex document, it means that always the context changes.
Paul: Probably in 2 to 3 pages, again, the context changes. Two to three pages, again, everywhere. It means that, really, it's not sticking to the same context, or somehow, totally, the context has changed. In those type of use cases, I feel that semantic is better.
Paul: Otherwise, for other use cases, I won't see that semantic chunker is really. Because I have seen a lot of videos in YouTube, they say semantic, by default, close your eyes and use it.
Paul: But really, it should not be like that. You have to understand the situation, and then only you pick it up. Because it comes with a cost.
Paul: Even in production, if you're using it, it means that you have to host that embedding model somewhere. Right now, I have done it in my local.
Paul: But in production, you have to do the hosting.
Paul: So, always remember that.
Paul: like the annual report of a company, but you have to, again, analyze the document. Blindly. I know that in that annual report, most of the information will be there with respect to the company.
Paul: Okay, all the information, at least I know some things will be submitted.
Paul: So, really, like, this is good, but again.
Paul: Now, here, let's try to look into the initialization and the parameters here, a little bit, in the semantic chunker. So, here, chunker, semantic chunker, first of all, you decide what type of model that you want to use. So, this is a MinisLab motion-based strategy to embed, so this model is also a good one.
Paul: Then you select a threshold, which is 0.8. The threshold similarity must be between 0.1. So, maximum tokens per chunk. Now, this number, you can simply play with. It totally depends. So, like, 2048 is the max limit. Try to stick around 1000.
Paul: Similarity window. Okay, so by default, this is 3. So, in our implementation, we never use this similarity window. So, window for similarity calculation. Now, this is important, and most of the times, like, out of 3 times calculation, I can say that
Paul: Like, taking an odd number is always important here. It can be 5, it can be 7, but don't take even numbers.
Paul: Skip Windows, so by default, every time we skip Windows, we don't try to merge any information.
Paul: No, with the skip and the march, so this is the cool, the vanilla version here.
Paul: Okay, enabling merging of similar non-conceptive groups, so if you want to skip this particular information, it means that if you feel that in some cases, the same sentences has to be there in two different channels. In those cases, you can use a skip window, otherwise, really, I don't use skip window a lot.
Paul: Okay, now these are all bit testings, but, with, semantic chapter, I will say that it works really good, and this is the main guy. Okay, you can look into a few of the implementations of red grammat.
Paul: This is the actual guy. So, he has a really good, like, content who has the core implementation, and even he took the idea from a Twitter tool.
Paul: Now, this one.
Paul: Multi-topic, it's not about multi-topic. Always remember the topic should have different context, then only it is important.
Paul: Otherwise, it is not important. If you have a multi-topic also, but if you have structure.
Paul: Where you feel that you have less structure, okay, so generally for unstructured data, I've seen, it means that, really, like, you cannot put some rules.
Paul: In those cases, it is helpful.
Paul: Okay, if you have a structure, you know that you can use rules, but if there is no structure, really, how you can define the rules?
Paul: Then only, then come the concept of split the sentences.
Paul: Otherwise, Y will split, if you have some logic to apply.
Paul: Always remember that, because this is actually a mess again. When you will do your experiment with semantic chunkers, even for you, I will say, if you want to use it in production, first, don't always go for it in one shot. If nothing is working, then only go for this particular solution.
Paul: Okay, because, Surreal, it comes with the cost. Again, if you…
Paul: It even has few problems, okay? When your data becomes very, very big.
Paul: Somehow, it means that, more the data, the latency will be very, very high for your chunking strategy unit.
Paul: It means that your chunking might take 20 minutes or 30 minutes.
Paul: Okay, so for this, again, a dedicated machine or an instant that needs to be done. You cannot do everything through Lambda.
Paul: Okay, because… so you have to understand, from intra-side also, if you are actually going with this particular implementation.
Paul: It takes more computational resources.
Paul: Now, coming to late jumping now, this is, a new one.
Paul: Till now, how many of you know about late chunkers? Anybody has heard about late chunkers?
Paul: It means that, initially, it won't do charging.
Paul: It will do the chunking later on, after creating the embeddings.
Paul: Anybody else heard about late chunkers? Really? I don't use it in production, but this feature is also available.
Paul: Okay, now, when I'm talking with respect to late chunkers, so split the text into chunks based on lead-bound token count.
Paul: Now, you have to understand late chunking. So, there are two types of chunking. One is called the pre-chunking and the post-chunking concept. These things comes under post, pretty much. Now, in post-chunking, when I'm talking, it means that you pass the entire document.
Paul: To create the embeddings.
Paul: Now, the portion comes, okay, you pass the entire documents to create the embeddings. Now, based on the embeddings, you will be creating the charts. Little bit, the strategy is different.
Paul: Okay, now, really, like, late chunkers, I have never used it in production, but again, I feel that Alright.
Paul: It's against that golden rule of Iraq.
Paul: Somehow, because I know that's better… it's better always to create chunks before and then only proceed ahead. Now, late chunking, let's a little bit talk about this particular approach, because these are something new concepts. Similarly, neural chunker is there, and slumber chunker. These two are somewhere new, and I feel that it is important.
Paul: Because these are a little bit advanced, but we all don't always use these type of options in our production directly.
Paul: So, let's get back to our iPad. Where is my iPad?
Paul: Alright, I think everybody can see.
Paul: Now, from here, The first one…
Paul: That is our late channel. Okay, so probably, let's take a simple example. Okay, just wait.
Paul: think I can copy this image.
Paul: Little bit about the workflow that I'll be talking here.
Paul: Okay, and now I'll be talking about that pooling concept. Pooling comes in semantic, chunking also, so a little bit about that pooling strategy. So, when you look into this image, okay, so what is the first thing that you look here?
Paul: Try to look into from this direction, this direction.
Paul: Don't look from top to bottom. Try to look from bottom to top.
Paul: So, first of all, you have that…
Paul: you will be embedding the entire document, okay, using a long context model. So, now the requirement here is a long context. If you have a small context, really, you cannot apply this one. So, generally, long context when I'm telling what type of models you will pick up, guys.
Paul: Yes, generally, what type of… models.
Paul: Anything more than 1 million.
Paul: Always remember, the context window, it has to be more than 1 million.
Paul: Okay, that is bare minimum that I am telling, but if you feel that if you have small documents.
Paul: Okay, but majorly, like, entire document, so I'm thinking about a really big, big document here right now.
Paul: Okay, now, once you will be first embedding the entire document, so you have to always work with the
Paul: Like, a long context window model, then comes chunk of the embeddings, not the text.
Paul: Now, this concept is really new, okay? And, when to use this one? Because, really, how many of you think that chunking of the embeddings
Paul: Because till now, nobody has discussed about this one.
Paul: Here's it, guys.
Paul: Because right now, we are going against our normal strategies. Okay, we are exploring something which is pretty much new. Right now, in 2025, only this came.
Paul: Because here, First of all, we have to understand why late chunking was introduced.
Paul: the main problem, or basically to solve a common problem, which is context loss. Okay, the main idea of bringing
Paul: this late… chunky.
Paul: It was based… One… one major problem.
Paul: Which is context loss.
Paul: That's why it's a research you have to understand.
Paul: This type of implementations, it's not like that every time you will use it.
Paul: Okay, now this is much more recent, so I thought about, let's talk a little bit about that.
Paul: So, in any type of chunking, whatever that we have learned till now, everywhere there is a problem of context loss.
Paul: Okay, now, context clause. In simple example, let's try to understand, in any chunking strategies that you have done, when you split a document first, okay, and then create embeddings, can I say that each chunks becomes isolated?
Paul: Yes or no?
Paul: When you split a document first, and then create the embeddings, can I see that each chunks becomes isolated?
Paul: If the chunks are isolated, what will happen? It will result in ambiguous or contextuals.
Paul: within the chunk.
Paul: Always remember that.
Paul: Okay, now, this is a common problem, but it's… Not like that.
Paul: Okay, so, like, if you have some type of isolated Chunks.
Paul: Okay. Because of this, two major problems that you two face. One is, Ambiguity?
Paul: and context loss. The idea was to solve these two particular problems, because of that.
Paul: your, late chunking came. Now, this is a backward-based implementation.
Paul: Okay, the lead changing is simply toward backwards. Instead of splitting the text word, okay, we start by feeding the entire document into a long context embedding one.
Paul: Okay, now this… no, when you are working with long context embedding models, what will happen?
Paul: Okay.
Paul: embedding model.
Paul: No, really, in the market, there are not a lot of long context.
Paul: Okay, like, really, Gemini is not good in these type of use cases.
Paul: So, you have to understand, the first one, when I'm talking with Elsie.
Paul: What will happen?
Paul: First, token-level embeddings.
Paul: Okay, the first step is token-level embeddings.
Paul: In this entire journey of RAG, or in this course, have you ever created token-level embeddings?
Paul: We have always used chunk-level embeddings, guys. Remember that, don't get confused. Okay, because this is our… against the traditional approach, so little bit new things that are there.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: And then you will actually split the document into chunks. First, token-level embeddings, okay, and then you do the splitting operation.
Paul: Now, the question comes, when you create the embeddings for each channel, okay, you will use the token-level embeddings, okay, that were already created with the full context. Now, what is the purpose of this token-level embeddings? Now, they will have full context.
Paul: Yeah, so when you pass your entire document into a long context embedding model, okay, now that will create your token-level embeddings. Now, token level and a full context, it means that the full picture, also, you can think about.
Paul: And exactly what is there with respect to the document, everything it will understand.
Paul: Once you have this full context, then only you will do a split operation.
Paul: So, first of all, that, context understanding.
Paul: They have focused much more here.
Paul: So, when we create the embeddings for each chunk.
Paul: Okay, so we will use that token-level embedding.
Paul: That we have created, where full context was there.
Paul: can simply, then Google.
Paul: Take the average.
Paul: Okay. Now, simply in this step, what we can take, we can take the average of the relevant token emittings of that chunk.
Paul: In this way, they have proved, but really not on every type of data. I find that this particular approach is really useful.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: Average the token embeddings.
Paul: Now, let's try to look into this picture, the same thing that they are trying to refer here. So, first of all, enter the document using a long context model.
Paul: Chunk the embeddings, not the text, reserve the context before the embeddings were created, with full document context.
Paul: Now, each document remembers its relation to the neighboring chunks.
Paul: Now, really, like, in the way that they think about the neighboring chunks, it means that, see, now, this particular embedding, okay, now, I can say that this has a relationship with this somehow, with this somehow, with this sum.
Paul: Then again, with this somehow, with this somehow. So, I know that, okay, the surrounding information.
Paul: Now, when you try to do this, how many of you think that the concept of chunk overlap will be, like, important here? Because in your traditional approach, you have taken that chunk overlap for context preservation across your chunks. But can I say that in this case, you don't need that chunk overlap concept only?
Paul: See, that's why, because this is really, like, very late implementation we do it, but really, like, this is an interesting concept that I feel.
Paul: And generally, like,
Paul: The use case for late chunking is very specific, when you have complex relationship-based documents. Okay, in those cases, it's really helpful.
Paul: So, first of all, it will preserve the context.
Paul: the token-level embedding, so this embedding is actually token-level embeddings, guys.
Paul: Okay, with the full document context, each chunk remembers the relationship. Now, coming to pooling.
Paul: Let's talk about this particular concept, pooling, first of all. So, pooling, strategically, instead of pulling all tokens into a single vector, late chunking pool tokens according to your chunking strategy to get multiple context-aware embeddings per document, okay? But before that, you have to understand what is pooling.
Paul: So, in simple terms, let's talk about pulling.
Paul: So, right here, we'll be talking about mean pooling much more, because there are more than 10…
Paul: 10 types of pooling, but really we are not focused on. Mean pooling is the actual one.
Paul: That we will be focusing.
Paul: Any type of other coolings that you can randomly guess, guys? Anyone?
Paul: Because in convolutions, if you have heard about that.
Paul: mean, max, average, okay, no. Here, this thing changes in, transformers.
Paul: Alright, now, with respect to this… Pooling, in simple terms.
Paul: Pooling generally, is applied on top of a tokenized operation.
Paul: Okay, so let's try to understand where it fits, because everywhere it is applied, but nobody actually talks about it.
Paul: Okay? Now, first of all, let's try to understand where pulling fits. So, first of all, I will take a piece of text.
Paul: Now, generally, what happens in NLP? Once you have the text, or the text chunk for now, then I can say that some type of tokenizer that I have applied
Paul: Yes or no?
Paul: Now, that tokenizer goes into some types of encoder, Which will throw you… and embedding.
Paul: Yes?
Paul: Now, this is a core NLP flow. Now, after this encoder, this is where pooling happens.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: Now, in simple terms, what is pooling?
Paul: Pooling is a compression technique.
Paul: Okay? In simple terms, it is a compression technique.
Paul: So this is basically a method to compress token-level embeddings.
Paul: Now, by default, this is applied on any type of transformer, sentence transformer-based model.
Paul: I think you guys have worked with Sentin Transformers?
Paul: Okay, so compressing token-level embeddings, into.
Paul: Okay, so you'll be, like, completing, multiple tokens into a single fixed-size vector.
Paul: This is very, very important, guys, because in every embedding model.
Paul: If I say that, in a chunk.
Paul: If you have, 300 tokens.
Paul: So, generally, what happens when you do a token-level embedding.
Paul: So generally, if I say I have in one chunk, you have?
Paul: 300 tokens.
Paul: First, this will be getting converted into 300 embeddings. Yes or no?
Paul: This is not a single fixed-size vector.
Paul: Do you think that this is a single fixed-size vector?
Paul: Because if we don't do pooling, okay, we won't have one vector, because if we don't apply that this is a default setting.
Paul: By default, what happens?
Paul: I can say that one vector is per token.
Paul: Which is really unsuitable, like, this is totally unusable for retribut.
Paul: Because in this particular approach, you really cannot find anything.
Paul: For any type of document retrieval type of task. Now, this single vector that you have, this information, you save it where? In your vector DB.
Paul: Now the question comes, does token-level embedding sign means that all right?
Paul: Because how many of you, how many of you knew about this? Because this concept generally comes when you teach transformers, yes?
Paul: Because, first, you have the original piece of text, that converts into a tokenizer, then you pass it to an encoder. From the encoder, you'll be getting the token embeddings.
Paul: Once you have the token, level embeddings, then you apply pooling. So, through pooling, what you do, so this is basically a compression technique. From token-level embeddings, it means that you convert your 300
Paul: tour, Single vector.
Paul: Because this single vector is only imported in our rack part.
Paul: So that's why it's very, very… so, pooling is very, very critical, I can say technique, but really, nobody talks about. Now, if I'm talking from pooling perspective, the major one, I am talking about mean pooling, so all the discussion that I have done. Now, mean pooling means what? Mean means
Paul: Average.
Paul: So, average pulling.
Paul: Now, for the calculation of this 300 to a single vector, so what you will do, if I do a chunk embedding… now see, guys.
Paul: this chunk embedding that I'll be doing.
Paul: Okay, so let's take… so here I will take, like,
Paul: a lot of N, the total number of tokens. Okay, now this chunk embedding that I'm calculating.
Paul: Okay, so here I'll be passing my main formula, so let's take i is equal to 0 to n.
Paul: Okay, and here, our embedding.
Paul: Now, this is how we'll be performing an average operation. Now, this will calculate what? Average…
Paul: up all… token.
Paul: level embedding.
Paul: Okay, and generally, like, I can say this is a good way, but in RAG, only your mean pooling is used.
Paul: There are other pullings also. XCLS pulling is there, okay, but Max pulling is also there.
Paul: Now, generally, if you have worked with NER-based solutions, like named entity, where you try to find
Paul: Different type of NKTs.
Paul: In that case, we use Macs.
Paul: Okay, so similarly, you have attention-weighted pooling also. But for now, in your rack, this is the core concept.
Paul: generally how to convert your token-level embeddings. Now, this is where your, late chunking comes into the picture.
Paul: Because these token-level embeddings, when you actually do it.
Paul: Can I say that this token level emitting where I kept it, this will be having your full context, yes or no?
Paul: Yes or no, because during… when you are creating the embedding, there is also some amount of information loss. This you have to understand.
Paul: I cannot say that after creating the embedding, I will be getting, because if you try to perform a meme, or a meme pooling operation, in that case, it, like, always creates…
Paul: a very small amount of problem. I cannot say a very big, but it's a very important one. Now, this particular concept that we have discussed of mean pooling, it is applied immediately all the models of sentence transform.
Paul: How many of you have used Sentence Transformer?
Paul: this particular package.
Paul: this package, I think everybody has used.
Paul: Okay, so, like, by default, in every sentence transformer model, meme pooling is by default applied, okay? You don't need to apply it from your own site.
Paul: Okay? So, in simple terms, if I say, what is pooling? What will guys say? So, pooling, is a simple method through which you convert your token-level embeddings into a single vector.
Paul: Okay.
Paul: I think everybody understands now what is pooling?
Paul: Because this is a representational decision, you have to understand, generally in NLP and academic terms, we call this a representational change.
Paul: Roeth is asking, wouldn't it create noise? This is how every embedding model works. So, what you thought about embedding models, Roeth, till now?
Paul: Every embedding model, whether it's, like, now, the pooling strategy.
Paul: can be modified, because, as you can see, mean, max, so average can move into some other metric, okay, but majorly in everywhere. In everywhere, this concept is there. Now, generally, when we deal with embedding, then only we talk about these approaches.
Paul: Alright, fine. Now, let's move ahead with our chunking.
Paul: Now, so, in this part, so preserving the context.
Paul: Because the embeddings were created with full documents, so this is the token-level embedding, actually. So when full context, when you were referring.
Paul: Now, you have to understand who has a better context, if I really say. Token level embedding, or the direct embedding that you do after pulling.
Paul: Just tell me.
Paul: So, if I say, if you try to compare token-level embeddings with your normal embeddings, which has… so, really, in every embedding model, when you say that, I'm doing, for example, I'm working with 384.
Paul: Or 786, okay, or 1536. Or 307. So, this… what type of embeddings are these?
Paul: These are pooled embeddings.
Paul: It means that an average operation has been applied.
Paul: whenever you apply an average operation, there has to be some type of infoloss. Always remember that.
Paul: anywhere. If you try to perform any type of average or mean operation, there has to be some type of influence.
Paul: Oh, no, I think, okay, now let's get back here. Now, based on this implementation, so you can see, pulling strategically, instead of pulling all tokens into one vector, late chunking, just focus on this.
Paul: Pull tokens according to your chunking strategy to get multiple contexts.
Paul: our embeddings per document. Okay, now, this thing, let's try to look through our implementation.
Paul: Chunking, chunking… no, really, like, chunking is such a topic, no, if you try to go in depth, it might take more than 3 months only to discuss chunking.
Paul: But, these concepts are important.
Paul: How many of you feel that these concepts are important? Because really, if you are an application applied guy, not so much. If you're an R&D guy, then only it is important.
Paul: I think…
Paul: Yes, like, if you're an application guy, really, like, a simple dev guy, not… but R&D guy, yes, I feel that this is important.
Paul: Alright.
Paul: And now, see, now this late stencer implementation I have taken from here, and generally the concept of pooling changes, okay? So, like…
Paul: even,
Paul: So there is one interesting concept in 2025. If you have time, you can look into attention-based pooling. That concept is also really…
Paul: a new one, but I feel that probably in the next few years, it might change a lot of things.
Paul: Alright, now, let's take our, late checker from here.
Paul: Okay, so… chunking. Where is my anti-gravity here?
Paul: Okay, so… now, the core purpose is not to lose context.
Paul: Okay, so now this is a backward way of moving ahead. So, generate the document-level embeddings. See, document-level embeddings refer to that token level. Within your documents, what are there? At the end of the day, within your documents, there are tokens. Okay, now before chunk.
Paul: Now, the core implementation here, directly, it has been applied. Okay, now…
Paul: Here, a Nomix model has been used. Okay, so again, I think a download operation that will go ahead.
Paul: So, let's see…
Paul: And from here, the late chunker.
Paul: Okay, so…
Paul: Now, majorly, if you see here, if you, look into the rules, the chunk size, this is one parameter selecting of the embedding model.
Paul: Then comes your recursive rules. Recursive rules are the default ones, like paragraph, lines, sentences based on that. And minimum characters per chunk. Okay, so, like, minimum characters that needs to be defined, 24. This is the default one, but please try to go with a higher number. I feel that this is towards always the lower side.
Paul: Now, a little bit with respect to the core implementation, because, this late chunking, agentic chunking, and LLM chunking, these three are a little bit new, but I feel that, yes, it can be used.
Paul: Now, when you try to look into this value, this late chart.
Paul: How many of you skilled at this graph you guys have seen before? Somewhere.
Paul: just try to look into the graph. Somewhere you might have seen exactly not the values.
Paul: But, yes, there can be some changing.
Paul: So you have to really… because when you look into the graphs, you get a better perspective, okay? You will try to look into. So, here I can see that, yes, the median value has decreased. The target was 512, but here it's 441.
Paul: Now, if you really look into, right here, based on chunk 1, the characters are coming 488, chunk 2, 488,
Paul: Or write chunk 3 again, somehow.
Paul: This is coming, okay, and let me look into it.
Paul: So, 3 chunks, so here, 488, and right now, the file that I have passed, okay, so that technical document text.
Paul: this particular file.
Paul: Here, because this is a complete version, I will say that this output is somehow better, that I have felt, as compared to a semantic one. Here, it is somewhere close to our target.
Paul: So I will say that, yes, this is good. The token count, somehow, it is at least the minimum count that we have as close to 217.
Paul: And the max says 509. So, based on the text document, I can see that this is performing in a better way.
Paul: As compared to our other approaches that we have taken, then…
Paul: Okay, now this is somehow, like, close to, I can say, recursive, or our… the results are very close to our recursive character, or our recursive chunker.
Paul: Okay, and this is a compressed version with a single outlier here, and if you really look into the standard deviation… now, what has happened to the standard deviation?
Paul: Can I say that this has really increased, like, now, totally?
Paul: The standard deviation, and if you look into the mean and the medium.
Paul: the mean and the medium, 400. Now, these values will help you to make a lot of inference. Now, when you look into the standard deviation of 112, what it tells.
Paul: Simply, like, lower standard, deviation, I told that, lower standard deviation, is equal to, like, more predictable token.
Paul: usage per channel, but if your Chinese aviation is towards your higher side, it is always less predictable. Directly when I cannot say or I cannot predict, okay? You really look into and analyze each answer, then only you can see.
Paul: Now, the other thing around highly consistent chunking, I cannot say that.
Paul: Because… Can I say that this is highly consistent chunking?
Paul: To some point, I can say that, yes, it is highly consistent, but again, the rule that we have known, generally, like, 20%.
Paul: But here, really, 112.
Paul: So this is how much percentages it is coming. Can I say that 40% of the mean.
Paul: 40% of the mean is really an impactful value, guys.
Paul: Generally, this value should be lower somehow.
Paul: Now, we need to fix this, because somehow, probably, we have to manipulate the data. That is the only way around, or probably by changing some rules.
Paul: But I feel the standard deviation should always be less than
Paul: That 30% mark. Somehow, it has crossed at 40, but again, the approach that we have learned till now, most of the things are applied on that traditional technique, which is pre-chunking.
Paul: Okay, but this is actually a post-chunking strategy, where you do the chunking later point after creating your token-level embedding segment.
Paul: So, in this strategy, really, that rule doesn't get applied of standard deviation, of having that 30% error.
Paul: So here, ESN varies. I can say the variability or the spread around the mean is towards the higher side, that's why the drop we can see. Previously, the mean was around, like, 505, if you try to look our initial chunkers, that we have… where somehow they will be having higher mean. Here, 505.
Paul: In sentence, it was 471. It was having those higher values, 478. But somehow, this time, it has decreased. But again, it has not decreased a lot, like this one, semantics, 56. Having mean of 56 is really bad, guys.
Paul: Okay, but at least it has performed better than the other one. This is just, like, in our use case, I can say that, yes, it has performed better than our semantic chunky, based on the data that we have taken.
Paul: Alright, I think, let's keep it till this point, only two chunkers are there, we can discuss it tomorrow.
Paul: Because after tomorrow, move so much chunk, okay? Now, a simple task that I'm giving you, okay,
Paul: try to do it by today. Now, this implementation, as we have taken it, okay.
Paul: a simple implementation of semantic one. Try to create a very similar implementation, don't use any fancy libraries, just use NumPy, SQLearn, Transformers, these slightly. Okay? And then try to implement the late chunker by yourself.
Paul: How many of you can do it?
Paul: Yes or no? How many of you can do it?
Paul: Because, see, little bit then tomorrow, like, whoever is sharing, okay, then we will go through that.
Paul: There is nothing to try. People are telling us, we'll try, we'll try, there is nothing, just be smart. Okay, first of all, go to GitHub, Chunky.
Paul: Always try to decode source code. Don't say try, try.
Paul: It's not about trying. Okay, simply go to the SRC file, directly look into the package.
Paul: Now, from here, go to that chunker folder.
Paul: Okay? Now go into the sled.
Paul: dot P1. You have the entire source code.
Paul: Okay, not a lot of lines also, only 190 lines, and remove those logger lines, it would be less than 150.
Paul: Okay, and if you really look into the late chunker as actually getting the properties, or inheriting the properties from your recursive chunker.
Paul: Always try to look into the source code.
Paul: Then only you will understand, okay?
Paul: I think everybody can do it now, guys.
Paul: Because now, it's nothing…
Paul: Because the source code's also I have shared, but you have to just be smart and just use NumPy, or you can use PyTorch also, I have no issue. But try to do a rough implementation, at least.
Paul: It's not necessary, you have to exactly match, but that approach that we have taken. Because this is that opposite technique. It means that it yields the rules that we have learned then.
Paul: Okay, that's why. Just focus. And then, two chunkings, I think agentic and LLM is the remaining. So, agentic and LLM, so, two things. Neural chunker. Neural chunker, so you can see, split using a fine-tuned, BERT model. Okay, and then you have slumber.
Paul: Okay, now this is the agentic chunker that we have…
Paul: So this is an agent-based approach where you can define. So tomorrow, I think we can talk about these implementations, but always look into the core part, because this, library is really small, so you can… because even I also look into the, core.
Paul: Because, actually, how the implementations are there?
Paul: And it's open source, so please at least have a look.
Paul: All right.
Paul: Yes, yes, you don't need logger lines. You just keep the core implementation. I need the core part. Anybody, whoever, it's not about trying.
Paul: Now, E2317 is saying, can you tell about the task? Not only I told about the task.
Paul: Just try to do a scratch implementation of Blit Chunker.
Paul: Handshake, through Handshake, you pass on the data, Taran Teja.
Paul: from Chompey to your vector TV.
Paul: Alright, now let's start taking some questions.
Paul: Because going forward, Rajat, Satish, you will have with your hand.
Paul: lose this.
Rajat Khanna: Yeah, highball.
Paul: Okay, and just wait, rarian is asking, what was the purpose of introducing… see, now, these are strategies.
Paul: Ariane, really, like, I'm trying to cover the latest strategies till now in 2025, whatever has came.
Paul: Now, there is no such purpose. In some cases, late chunking might work for you. And generally, like, winning field that, in most of the chunk.
Paul: any chunkers that you are applying, okay, you are losing, the context, okay, or you feel that the query that you were asking were not getting the correct results. In that case, you can change your chunk.
Paul: Because, see, everything can be changed. That was the main purpose. When you try to build a rag.
Paul: That is a mean problem, it's basically everything is a hyperparameter.
Paul: Okay, now, out of this hyperparameter, you need to test it.
Paul: And I don't prefer to use always semantic and late, because they always come with the costs.
Paul: So, not a fan on that one.
Paul: Okay, but again, it might help you.
Paul: I'll hope you get that on.
Paul: Yeah, budget.
Rajat Khanna: Yeah, Hepal. First of all, Happy New Year.
Rajat Khanna: So…
Paul: Yes, Boomika, all that.
Rajat Khanna: So my, first request is, like, try… please attach these iPad notes, in the Notion.
Paul: Added nope, I will attach it.
Paul: Okay. Both notes, last class and tutorials, this only, I will attach it.
Rajat Khanna: Okay. And, the second is, if, I remember correctly, in starting off this course, so you showed us a website, in that we're just pasting some text, and it will show us how the different sizes of chunks are curated when we change the numbering from 500 to.
Paul: Yes, that is chunk peas. Chunk fees, chunk piece, yes.
Rajat Khanna: Yeah, so I think we can take a reference for those in the current class, because it was most of the theory in current class, so…
Paul: There, you don't have the implementation of this chunkers only.
Rajat Khanna: Correct, correct, correct, I know. Just to get the reference, like, we are implementing the chunkers as in coding, and just to understand the output.
Paul: What? So, why you need that chunk bees? That part I didn't get.
Rajat Khanna: No, just to understand, like, we are providing our, context, context as in text, to our… this code, we are changing the dimension size, overlap, and all those things, and then the output, is visible in the graphs if we can try to use NumPy Pandas.
Paul: No, no, see, there, those type of chunkers are not available only. There, it's fixed token, and only recursive. See? Okay, okay, got it. I can show you right now only. I got your question, you thought about other chunkers might be available there.
Rajat Khanna: Yes, yes.
Paul: Not others are their children with…
Paul: This is created by Craig Cram currently. Now, when you go into this, the, just wait.
Paul: Now, when you go into this scene, you have this only, recursive and character, others are not available.
Rajat Khanna: Okay.
Paul: That's why I didn't pay the sum. I showed you that time.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, got it, got it.
Paul: will get the basic idea of checking, that's why I covered it in the initial piece.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, got it. And, the lastly, like, the team building, so, like, team building as in what kind of project we will be making, making, so…
Rajat Khanna: Can you give.
Paul: I think last class, people told about that AWS certification, a few people will be doing. Yeah. Okay, so I know, like, in class, like, Mutatha is there, he is really good in AWS.
Paul: But at least I will discuss the architecture with him, and then I will probably ask him, like, how much he can contribute based on that. So, similarly, I know a few people. Okay, based on that, I will ask them. It's not like I will ask everybody.
Paul: Because at least for this, you should be good in AWS. The entire stack that I'm planning, it's completely AWS. It means that you won't be out of AWS.
Rajat Khanna: Thank you.
Paul: It means that totally everything AWS.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, it's not a project that we are building, creating a team internally, and we will be.
Paul: It means that somebody in your… in this, some members will create it.
Rajat Khanna: Rest of them, you can take the learning from that.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, okay, okay.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, yeah, thank, no, thank you.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah, hi, Paul. So, I think, you answered the question that I was about to ask. Basically, how would the others get the exposure to the project?
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: which would be worked by only a limited set of people, right? So…
Paul: It will be limited, CC, it will be open source, you will be having the access to it, and probably I'll be keeping a session to explain
Paul: others that exactly what the team is building and what is the idea. That part, I will be making it clear. But some team, it's not like everybody. See, everybody I don't know.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Hmm.
Paul: It's not possible, like, I cannot evaluate by taking a test or something.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah, right.
Paul: Because I know people who are good for them.
Paul: But those are the least kind.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah. Definitely not that.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: That's, fine. I'm sorry, I've got one more, question, so…
Paul: Go ahead, go ahead.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: This is related into chunking only, so, I've got a use case coming up in the place that I work, which, you know, majorly, the major focus would be on, creating a scalable vector DB.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: You know, wherein the data from multiple data sources flow in, and…
Paul: a vector DV is totally different.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: I mean… VectorDB that supports the data for different objectives, getting data from different data sources.
Paul: No, that is, you see, getting data from different data sources, that is a different problem.
Paul: Building a vector TV is a different problem, that's why.
Paul: It means that you want to build your own quadrant, you want to build, that is…
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: No, no, I'm sorry, utilizing a vector DB, that would, you know, be scalable, I mean… Yeah.
Paul: scalability see any defector database? Right now, I feel the best one for scalability in market is Millverse.
Paul: Okay, but quadrant is also good, because right now, whenever we scalable, it means some billions will be there, probably you will be having 10 billion, 20 million, 100 billion in those cases. When I know that the number of vectors in my use case, it surpasses, like, more than 50 billion at least, I try to go initially with Milverse.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah.
Paul: And I know that Quadrant and others will also work in that case.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah, that, that is fine. This is on the infrastructure level, but, you know,
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: it, you know, depend… we need to, like, choose the most appropriate chunking strategy. I know that it's experimentation all at.
Paul: I can't see.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Depending on the use case.
Paul: But then, how do you…
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah.
Paul: in Project 2, you have multi-data sources. There, I will be taking, like, one… like, say, there you have multiple file formats.
Paul: Like, probably, I'll be using DocLink, okay? And after that, I'll be applying chunking. Now, the question comes, for each document, you have one password.
Paul: Now, you will say that, okay, for docx files, I want to use this particular, chunking strategy. For my mountain files, this. For my SQL files, this. In that way, you have to define a rules.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah, okay, so… and also, how you store it will also matter, right? Because, see, if you have…
Paul: great.
Paul: See, once I convert them into vectors, I'll be saving them into VectorDB only, no?
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah, that's fine, but the sequence of those chunks has to be maintained depending on the use case, right? What if, you know, you wanna, like, ensure that the sequence doesn't get
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: should not mix, and the context flows correctly. So all that would be covered.
Paul: Okay, sequence, when you are talking, what do you mean by sequence? Sequence means document. Sequence comes with the document, whatever is there. We never change the sequence.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah. Within the document.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: But if… let's consider it's not a document, it's some, you know, text data itself, that you're getting, like a text file, and
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Basically, the…
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: text is linked to different types of metadata, wherein you would like to maintain the semantic structure of that, you know, so…
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Wow.
Paul: really, the thing that even I am not clear what you are asking. Okay, so, like.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yep.
Paul: Metadata, totally different. Out of context right now, okay? In VectorDB, with every chunk, you save the metadata.
Paul: That is for one chunk. Now, exactly, for the chunk, what is your requirement?
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: It can be different, multiple file sources, I got that.
Paul: Now, after that 5 sources… now, for each file sources, probably, like, we'll be using one each jumping strategy for each type of file types, okay? Now…
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Is that fine?
Paul: name change.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: The main thing is, see, within a source, for example, now we get, like, you know, all of our… all of our insights related to an event, okay? But then, we might…
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: those events happen multiple times across years, right? Now I get responses, so the user can
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Ask me to give me the summary of those responses for that single event, or for all the events that happened in the quarter.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: So the information… Related information might be spread across multiple events, or it will be just
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: You know, tied to a single event, so…
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: How would we… how should we consider chunking? You know, how do we apply chunking in that case?
Paul: So, when you say in the form of events, now, probably, I can say in one event, let's take… for one event, you have 10 files. In your second event, can I say that the number of files might have increased? In the third event, probably, more files came into the picture, or some file might got updated.
Paul: Are you talking about that scenario?
Paul: Because if you are talking about quarters, for example, initially I started the system of RAD. There, you have some quarterly information, quarter one. Then later on, you already got some information about quarter two. Then you got some information about quarter three. In that way, are you talking about…
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Yeah, but then imagine, sometimes I just wanna, like, you know, get the summary of quarter one, but sometimes I wanna, like, get the summary of quarter one, quarter two, quarter three, and, say, quarter one and quarter three have, related information.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: So… See, the way that you are telling…
Paul: whether it's quarter one, quarter two, that information, I can always keep it in my metadata. And through my filters, I can access it through quarters. That's how you define your metadata schema. It means that you don't need to look into your entire vector DB, just try to fetch that specific information, and through that, you can get it.
Paul: And later on, based on the grading, see, if you get the corrections… see, the main purpose is getting the correct chance.
Paul: Correct. And to get the correct terms, you need to work on the metadata. Now, based on your requirement, okay, now that, 5, because generally you need a 5-version system, if you… your data gets updated with time.
Paul: Now, probably, like, GitHub or something like that, who can track those things. You need to build a FCES of your own, okay, or based on that. Now, once you have that, you will be getting, because through metadata, you can get, whether for quarter one, quarter two, or if you have a single annual report also, let's take.
Paul: Where you have the information of all quarter one, quarter two. Then, definitely, during your metadata, when you'll be building that schema, you can take that information and later on, through filters, you can put it.
Bhoomika Nanjaraja: Oh, okay, got it. Thank you. Yeah, makes sense.
Paul: Alright.
Paul: I guess more thought of.
Murtuza Saifee: Yes. I will opinion you, first of all, and .
Paul: Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Murtuza Saifee: Thanks.
Murtuza Saifee: Thanks for the session. So, I would like to really thank you, because the details that you have gone through, and the, you know, the things that you are going in detail, it is really helpful, because you won't find any details so easily, so I'd really like to thank you on this one.
Paul: Normal price.
Murtuza Saifee: I do have a couple of questions. Actually, I, one thing, I'm not familiar with Llama Index a lot, so I was just learning from you on this one. So, in Llama Index, you mentioned two things, right? So, in this class and in last class, we discussed the query engine.
Murtuza Saifee: And earlier, we also discussed the ingestion pipelines. So, what is actually the difference in those ones?
Paul: Query… see, query engine is where, like, you retrieve the context, and that you pass it to the LLM. Directly from that, you will be getting the response based on the modes that you select. Compact, reset. Okay. That is the only thing.
Paul: Inside a pipeline, in one shot, you can tell that, okay, now this is, my, like, multiple operations in one shot.
Paul: It means that, first of all, you will select in an ingestion pipeline, so, like, the data is incoming, so from which data source.
Paul: Then, on top of that, what embedding you want to apply. Once the embedding is applied, then the next vector store operation. So, all those operations of that rack, okay, it means that only that those data ingestion seeds, it means till that vector DB push.
Paul: Whatever the steps are, those things can only be applied.
Paul: It is nothing related to response, because there…
Murtuza Saifee: translation part, okay.
Paul: Yes, it's only the data ingestion pipeline, the phase one of the rack. It's not about the phase two. Phase 2 comes the query engine part, which is the last part, where you pass your retrib context from your vector TB to the other.
Paul: Okay.
Murtuza Saifee: Got it, got it. So here, in Lama Index, so it's very easy. So, like, you don't need to build a chain.
Paul: One of the things…
Murtuza Saifee: just involved.
Paul: Ubiquity.
Murtuza Saifee: engine, and that's it. Like, it's very simple.
Paul: It's clean. Like, I feel it's much more cleaner than land change.
Murtuza Saifee: Oh, yeah.
Paul: Little bit of more boiler-level code is repeated most of the times.
Murtuza Saifee: Yeah, because here we are not, so although in, behind the scenes, it's all of a query prompt and context, it's all passing it, but… so it's all wrapped and abstracted in a layer.
Paul: Yes, correct.
Murtuza Saifee: All right, perfect. So, thank you. The second question I want to confirm, so, in that, Chonky, so we are passing the tokenizers. So, in the tokenizers, we are, you said, so we'll be using the GP2 transformers, architectures for the tokenizer, right? So, because Chonky needs to tokenize, identify the tokens and process it, right?
Paul: it.
Murtuza Saifee: Will there be any other, or it will be always the GP2?
Paul: No, no, no, no, GPT-2 is the… the other one, there is a character tokenizer.
Paul: Okay, so, like, character is also there, but I feel GPT-2 is a widely used one, majorly.
Paul: Okay, now the question comes, you can bring your own custom tokenizer also. So, just wait, let me just show you the documentation. Chonk is, like, highly customized. So, for example.
Paul: If you use a very specific model, I think this is the one.
Paul: Now, see, in Transformers, if you have learned, simply see. Now, that's why I've taken this implementation from Tokenizer. Now, this is purely Hugging Face implementation. And see, you can bring your own custom tokenizer also, and that you can pass in.
Murtuza Saifee: Okay, alright, perfect. So, it provides all the details on that one.
Paul: Yes, like, that's why I told you, go through the documentation, like, really, like, I might miss a few things, but really, the documentation is really good, and it gives you next-level customization, which till now, neither Langchen, neither anyone has provided.
Murtuza Saifee: Okay, perfect. So, in… in the similar line, so, like, on… on the Llama Index, we… we discussed, so, like, you showed us the, customized query engine as well. So, those query engines, so, where you were mentioning, like, if you… if you will have some different, different, I think, retrievers.
Paul: Multiple type of retrievers when you have, then it's better to go through a custom query.
Murtuza Saifee: Custom, okay. All right. So, one last question, regarding… so, so the approach that you're taking it through is, like, each module, or each operations that happens in the RAG pipeline.
Murtuza Saifee: is kind of an isolated operations or isolated service. Like, ingestion, of course, we… even now on, like, how we do is we do have one data ingestion pipeline, so… or a service or microservice which is handling the data ingestion only. One service.
Murtuza Saifee: So, is only responsible for chunking, and then another one only responsible for, like, your vector store operations and those things. So, in this way,
Murtuza Saifee: you would suggest to design a REC pipeline, right? So, like, each component, with its own, it's a small blast radius, so that it doesn't affect the other components, and work in tandem, right?
Paul: Yes, that is the main rule. So, generally, like, but, I feel that that chunky part, like, very specifically, just keep the chunking part. If you feel that it's a separate microservice, generally through Lambda functions, I keep it.
Paul: Okay, like, whichever lambda function that needs to be info, based on that particular chunking part.
Paul: Generally, I prefer that through an event breach, like, whenever data comes, automatically.
Murtuza Saifee: Based on that.
Paul: Amazon text extract, okay, and then your metadata for metadata extraction, like Amazon Comprehend is there. Okay, so in that way, like, step by step one. But it's not every time necessary, just only for chunky, you will create a microservice. Okay, but the.
Murtuza Saifee: The reason why I…
Paul: Is that your data ingestion and indexing pipeline, it can be a single microservice or two microservices, depends upon the type of task that you are doing.
Murtuza Saifee: The reason why I ask, because, earlier to the Bumika's question, so where, let's say, if you have different, different types of data, different, different types of chunking that we want to apply, so I was thinking, okay, so chunking might be your black box, where, depending… so, of course, it's… the black box will only come once you will finalize your experience… experiment, sorry. So, this type of documents, by this type of data, I have, let's say.
Murtuza Saifee: 5-5 formats. Five types of data is going… coming onto my, checking service, and based on the data, it's gonna be processing its own checking, and then storing it to the vector store.
Murtuza Saifee: So that's… that kind of… I was just thinking.
Paul: Yes.
Murtuza Saifee: More into generalizing the process so that it can be reused, let's say, in other departments as well.
Paul: Yes, okay. Like, I got your point, like, we'll be talking about the service only. In the next project, little bit, at least the task that I'll be giving, it will be a very similar task.
Paul: Okay, so where the first phase will be only working in that pipeline, and, like, everything from AWS, only I was planning to insert.
Paul: Okay, so they are very… Thank you. Generally, for chanting, just be sure that, like, understand the document. After the document understanding happens, then for chanting, a lambda call will happen. Now, whichever, semantic, recursive, okay, generally, the decision, the main problem that I do face.
Paul: is, like, that document understanding, because semantic chunking, late chunking, every time I don't prefer using them, because they are a little bit, like, when something fails, then…
Paul: A manual… intervention is required. It means that if everything fails, then…
Paul: So, that part, automating is a little bit tough.
Paul: Okay, because really, like, if… just think about input tool.minmy system only, 50 type of file extensions will come, but 51 came into the picture.
Murtuza Saifee: Mmm.
Paul: Now, for… to handle that scenario, okay, it means that we need to… then, by default, we have to understand that file, so there only the problem is, if something comes out of the system.
Murtuza Saifee: Yeah, if it's a closed loop, it will be easy to manage, but if it's an open.
Paul: Yes.
Murtuza Saifee: You know, so, yeah, so I got your point. That will require some, of course, the manual intervention and continuous evaluation on this one.
Paul: Yes. It becomes an incremental process, that's why.
Murtuza Saifee: All right, perfect. Thanks, thanks, Paul. Thanks, I appreciate your time.
Paul: Alright, next… Who is there? I think Saurabh is there. Saurabh.
Saurav: Really high part.
Paul: Yes.
Saurav: Am I our new one?
Paul: Yes, yes, Saurabh, you are okay.
Saurav: Yeah, so my question is regarding the project. So, last time, the project, what we built.
Saurav: So, I remember, like, we used to upload a document, and based on, you know, that document ingestion, parsing everything, we were asking questions, right?
Saurav: So, my… I'm trying to correlate this rag with the, you know.
Saurav: data engineering stuff. So, in the production, how things, you know, go, like, you know, I want to ask, say.
Saurav: Usually in the data engineering projects, there will be a central repository where we will have all the, you know, data, all the documents, everything. And from there, we will be, you know, running the ingestion.
Saurav: and all the other transformation and other stuff, right? So, do we have any such projects where, you know.
Saurav: this data ingestion part. So, the kind of request I get, okay, like, you know, let's say clients come to me and ask.
Saurav: I have 1,000 documents in my, you know, shared drive, and now I want to build a RAG or a search kind of, you know, application.
Saurav: So, my question is, I mean, do we have, you know, any, some sort of projects where we, we actually see, you know, we don't have to manually upload anything?
Saurav: Let's say I have some documents currently in a repository, I do the ingestion, chunking, everything.
Saurav: And tomorrow, maybe, you know.
Saurav: Some more documents are coming, and incrementally, I need to process them and do the rest of the stuff.
Saurav: Who… who… who passes.
Paul: Yes, I got your question. Now, let's take an example for now. Let's simple. For example, you were dumping your data in S3.
Paul: Okay, it means that there is a cron job running every 24 hours, and based on that, updates are coming.
Paul: Okay, so generally, for example, I was working on that documentation part, so generally, I have webhooks. Okay, if any change comes inside a version control system, I'll be tracking that through a commit, and whatever the file changes, I'll be dumping it in Esk.
Paul: Now, wherever that happens, now, that S3 is here. Now, later on, you can switch it into data warehousing solution, because S3 is an example. Later on, according to your tool, or whatever that service that you want to use.
Paul: There is no restriction from that. But generally, like, from S3 or from your, any, solution where you want to pick it up, because these are raw documents, total.
Paul: Okay, so now comes, it can be in lake houses, anywhere, like, in Amazon glaciers, also, I have seen people kept it, but it totally depends upon the architecture. Now, if I take S3 for now, okay, and you are running a conjure, automatically the file comes.
Paul: Okay, every 24 hours, and the rest of the pipeline will be automatically invoked. You don't have to do anything.
Paul: Complete automation.
Saurav: But my question was the kind of project we built last time, right? So everything, let's say we had 5 modules, something was ingestion, embedding, right?
Saurav: So, if you are not decoupling each and every, every, you know, thing separately, right? The way we do in data engineering, let's say, ingestion is a separate pipeline, right? And then you are orchestrating it through some other, other third-party, maybe AFU or some.
Paul: I got your point, I got your point. For example, anything, like streaming data, Kinesis, Kafka, anything, how the data comes. Really, for me, it doesn't matter how the data comes.
Paul: For us, in most of the projects, we will assume the data is coming, because data engineering is not our focus.
Paul: You have to understand.
Saurav: I get that, but my part… my question is, how particularly I make sure, like, you know, the ingestion part runs, not the whole application.
Paul: It depends upon your use case. It totally depends. For example, if I say that through airflow, if you are talking about, okay, now, when your conjure will run.
Paul: It means that it has to detect some type of changes. That becomes completely your logic, no? How can I say that? In your use case, you have to run it only for 24 hours, perhaps every after 12 months?
Paul: Now, it is based on some webhook that you have decided, and through that, you will be dumping the data somewhere. Then comes your entire rack team that they will pull from that particular source, and rest of the rack pipeline will work.
Paul: I hope you get my point.
Saurav: I got it somehow, and my other question was regarding, do you have some, you know, guidelines or something for, estimation part? Okay, so let's say I have two
Saurav: factor a client's request, okay? And I have to break it into, you know, short of, you know, t-shirt sizing or something, right? In terms of complexity.
Saurav: the way we define in, you know, engineering projects or analytics projects. So, do you have something as a reference which, you know, people can
Saurav: utilize. My question is regarding, you know, let's say I have a requirement, right? So, how do I actually, you know, categorize it, whether it will be a simple, medium, complex, super complex, those kind of things?
Saurav: And if there is a standard guideline for, you know, estimating.
Paul: Now, the thing that you are asking, it depends upon organization to organization.
Paul: Okay, now there is no such fixed format. In our case, it might change now. For example, anything. It means that you are giving a pitch, and then probably you are working on a POC, and based on that, this is much more towards…
Saurav: It's like when you're bidding for a new project, right?
Paul: I got your point. Generally, for pitching purpose only, we talked at… I got your point, when you were actually approaching new clients.
Saurav: So, any guidelines or any documentation?
Paul: The thing that you are asking, it won't be with me.
Paul: Because…
Paul: Those documents, I do have some documents with me, but really, I need to look into it. Because my documents are a little bit different. It won't be from business perspective.
Saurav: That's right.
Paul: So I will daily, need to look into that.
Paul: Because few projects, directly. Because those documents, I think, Krish have much more access, rather than me. Few documents I have, but I will look into that.
Saurav: Yeah, and my last question is, is there a place where we can, you know, have a look on
Saurav: Reference architectures and, successful case studies, okay?
Paul: Why I'm asking is…
Paul: Every organization has their own use cases. There is no such a single website where you go in everywhere.
Paul: Simply.
Saurav: what I'm.
Paul: E.
Saurav: to ask is, usually, let's say you are a cloud engineer, right?
Saurav: So, in… let's say you talk about AWS. So, if I have to get the AWS reference architecture, you just search, and AWS presents you with hundreds of, you know, the architecture with services, people can read and at least get the…
Paul: the AWS blogs are there.
Saurav: Yeah, so similarly, for Azure also, we have, right, like, you have a problem
Saurav: some sort of case studies I'm talking about, right? So, why I'm asking about is, like, you know, when you read through the.
Paul: Every RAD service, whatever, till now, for example, pick up any VectorDB, like Quadrant, look into their blocks, everywhere there is a use case. Look into Elastic Catcher.
Paul: The Elastic team is widely using that one I know. Okay, they have very good, with respect to dense embeddings and sparse embeddings, really good blogs. Okay, because those are use cases from products. It means that somebody was their client, and they have actually published.
Paul: Okay, if you really want to… because those are stories. It won't be so much technical, because nobody will be talking about their.
Saurav: I mean, for senior candidates, you know, they need the kind of stories Success things, and, you know.
Paul: Yes, yes. The thing that you were asking in Amy, just pick up a service, try to look into their official, and you will be getting the blog and the products everywhere.
Paul: Everywhere, just look into quadrant blocks, the best places, everywhere, Milverse blocks, everywhere they have such solutions, because they talk about their client journey, what was the problem, and how they have solved it.
Paul: Elastic, like, I have gone through multiple use cases from the Elastic team.
Paul: I feel that, with their approach, because they have much more customized modules with them, as compared to others, but they have used those customized models, so you can look into it. It means that pick up the service, and based on that, you can get it.
Saurav: Okay, okay.
Paul: For this, you have to look into multiple services. It's not like in one place you…
Saurav: Yeah, yeah, yeah, so overall, holistic only, I'm asking, you know, like, I have to gain the overall idea of, you know, let's say there is a problem, what services, what tools, you know, what libraries I have to create, right? So, I should be able to,
Paul: Now, see, generally, they won't be talking about the architecture. They will be only talking… see, if a company has released their own blog, they will never open source the stuff, how they have built it.
Paul: They will only talk about the approach.
Paul: You have to read the story, and you have to get the approach.
Saurav: All right, yeah, yeah.
Paul: Okay. Because generally, like, every organization… I've seen very less who publish the entire solution or the entire architecture. They will tell they have used this component, this component, this component, what was the problem, and how they have overcome that.
Saurav: You've been wondering.
Saurav: Okay.
Paul: back home.
Paul: No… looking.
loki: Hi, Polly.
Paul: Yes.
loki: So, I was just going through the project videos again, and I was implementing it. When I implemented it, I got an image in ECR, and when I'm running it in the app runner, right, like, app runner is failing due to health check.
loki: I don't know how to proceed further. Even I got… I gave the variables in the app run itself. Still…
Paul: What are the logs, look into the logs, and what is the error that you are getting.
loki: Logs says L check, and in the inside logs, it's sharing, like, Pynton tick missing something, it's…
Paul: It is a Pythonic error, no? If you are getting a Pythic error, it means a Pythonic error.
Paul: If you can share me the screen and show me the GitHub action logs, from there only I can understand.
loki: Sure, I will share my screen.
Paul: Yes, Saurabh?
Paul: I think Zorav is done, E2317.
E2317: Hello, Paul. Paul, one question. In today's class, right? You have told about late Chankar and neural Chankar. So, for late Chankar, I am able to…
Paul: I have not taught till now.
E2317: For late chunker, right? For late chunker, you have, asked to download, like, Nomic AI, right? I have downloaded that locally.
E2317: through Hugging Face CLI. It's working right now, but that.
Paul: In case CLIV or download. If you execute that piece of code, automatically it will be.
E2317: Correct, but I'm getting a HTTP404 error.
E2317: on it.
Paul: HTTP, it means a connection issue.
E2317: Yes, like, how do I solve this? And I don't… I don't have any idea on this.
Paul: Okay, share your screen, because even internet issue or what?
Paul: some authentication issue also. Okay, share your screen. Both of you share your screen. Others can drop.
Paul: Ugh.
E2317: Are you able to see my screen?
Paul: Yes, yes, yes, no, till now, I cannot see your screen.
E2317: Okay.
E2317: There are too many files, so…
Paul: low-key, start sharing.
Paul: D2107, you also start sharing?
loki: I'm shutting my screen.
loki: I'll keep on re- rejoining Paul, like, because I, like, I just now gave access.
Paul: Okay, rejoin that resort.
E2317: Well, there is some issues, like, I'm not able to do it because my office has locked sharing. Can I share the logs there in the chat?
Paul: really, like, yeah, even Zoom has a, like, character limit. If you even paste that entire thing, I pasted it, let me see.
E2317: I'm getting this error, Paul.
Paul: Client error 404 not found, mozilla U.S. Talks…
Paul: Hugging Face API models, Nomic…
Paul: Because Nomic is directly available, you don't need to get any model access for this one.
Paul: Reliant error 404.
E2317: It's saying remote, entry not found error, 404 client ID request that it is giving.
E2317: Generally, verification, or whether something's getting blocked yesterday.
Paul: Just wait, because this is a transformer issue.
E2317: I'm getting this, I'm just… this was another…
Paul: Into state of speech… Sometimes gateway timeout error for the tokenizer, you might get it.
Paul: So, they are telling, there's not a valid model identifier.
Paul: Because in Gitam, the issues are written, but,
Paul: This is a duplicate of both the issues. OS error, alright.
Paul: This is your son working with.
Paul: Because in GitHub, the issues are mentioned, and everywhere it's telling it's an error from Hugging Face's side to me.
E2317: Okay, then I think I, like, for temporarily, probably.
Paul: fixable.
E2317: Local.
E2317: I think this is…
Paul: literally the error that you have is this URL…
Paul: Additional does not exist on main.
Paul: Does not exist on wind.
Paul: Yeah, a shortcut.
Paul: Okay, we had a short outage on the Hub website and the API earlier today, which is likely the result of…
Paul: This one…
E2317: This is…
Paul: 504… I'm looking into… 404…
Paul: experienced a bug, which means popular organizations had their own model temporarily disappear from the hub. Yes, it looks like such an issue, because, see, I'm also sharing the GitHub issue.
Paul: Just try to click on the link, from here you will get the idea.
E2317: book.
E2317: Shuh.
E2317: Thanks, Paul. Paul, last question I have before I wrap up.
Paul: Fantastic.
E2317: So, Paul, like, I'm new to the field of AI, right? Mostly from stats and ML background.
E2317: question is, like, like, what are the, like, initially, I have gone through a lot of content on LLMs. I have tried to code the entire LLM architecture from scratch.
E2317: I'm currently having 12 years of experience.
E2317: In consulting and core tech.
E2317: Now, question is, like, what should be my journey if I want to actually see forward? Like, because currently, when I'm working, but Paul, can I schedule a one-to-one call with you? Like, I want to…
Paul: Drop me a mail. Drop me a mail, then, like, I will share my Calendly with you, okay? Okay. And then, based on that, because again, my availability, that matters, so I will share that Calendly link again.
E2317: Sure, sure, I'll give you, whatever time suits you, I think.
E2317: You can let me know, I'm happy to join.
Paul: I don't think.
E2317: Okay, thank you, boy.
Paul: And before that, keep your resume with you, whatever that router version you have, the existing.
E2317: My current, current company is not updated, but, whatever I have, I'll just share my resume with you.
Paul: Oh.
E2317: Thank you, Paul.
Paul: Janika is asking, can you please check and guide Jenica, exactly what you want me to guide on?
Paul: Real Journika.
Paul: Loki, okay, Loki, I'm adding up to panelists, start sharing the screen.
Jainika: Alright, Paul.
Paul: Yes.
Jainika: Happy New Year, firstly. So, Paul, I have generated some code, so I'm able to understand what is, what is happening in this code, but I generate from the automatic generation. Is that fine for, like, organization point of view? Is that okay?
Paul: See, see, many organizations are using, like, tools. That is fine, but you have to understand, that is the main thing. Are you able to understand the code and the flow?
Paul: If you understand that thing, then there is no problem. Because later on, what happens? So, just think you have done something, you've taken a code snippet. Later on, if you need to do some modification, that's the main thing.
Paul: If you don't understand, modification becomes a bit harder.
Paul: It means that something, because… just because of a single logic, if you have to change in 10 different places, you have to understand this is connected with this model, this model, this model.
Paul: So that flow you have to understand, the control flow. If you know that, if you understand, then there is no issue. Because everywhere, in Deloitte, ENDY, I know many service-based, engineering, product-based, okay, they have given their employees subscription of Cursor, Otra, such tools, or Windsor, so… not a problem.
Jainika: Okay.
Jainika: That's all. Thank you.
Paul: Luki?
loki: I'm sharing my screen, but I'm not sure, like, now it was running fine, now it got deployed.
loki: Sharing my screen.
loki: Is my screen visible, Paul?
Paul: Yes, yes, I can see.
loki: Yeah, now, I think now… God, no.
Paul: However, 2 years, it worked.
loki: I'm not sure how… like, yesterday I was trying a beta, but it was failing.
loki: But now it got, and one more question, Paul. Like, I'm, I'm, preparing for this, Generative AI, professional exam. So, in Skill Builder, we have these courses, and we have this model deployment strategies.
loki: So, in case if I want to, like, everything is theoretical here. I don't… like, there are labs, but it's very limited. So, in case if I want to, get an answer on with this, like, how can I.
Paul: See, for this particular, okay, take that Stephanomach boots. I think that is the best place.
Paul: Because even as I was researching, as people asked the question, that, Steffenmark course in Udemy, okay, try to purchase it, because there are a lot of hands-on examples that are provided.
loki: Okay, Stefan Marca, yes.
Paul: That guy only creates courses on AWS only, like, he's at AWS main for all certifications.
loki: Okay.
loki: Can you ping me in the chatbot, like, the name?
Paul: Even I have to search in that department, I know.
Paul: Hello, who is…
loki: Thanks.
Paul: Just wait. I will share it while I'm searching right now.
loki: Yeah.
loki: And one more question, Paul. Like, in my current role, I don't, involve any… anything related to generative AI, but my target was to enter into any AI roles. So, like, if I'm going to an interview.
loki: should I need to, like, I have projects which are done in my local, but I have not done anything related to productionize, right? So, will that be a minor?
Paul: Thanks, David.
Paul: Yes, yes, yes, you go on.
loki: Yeah, will that be a minus point for me, Paul? Like, or should I need to tell that, yeah, I've worked, in, like, I need.
Paul: If you have really not worked, it becomes a minor point, you have to understand that.
loki: Okay.
Paul: Okay, it means that somehow, because in my one-to-one sessions also, I say that at least you have to showcase that you have worked on a PEOC in your previous organization.
loki: Oh.
Paul: Hence, because it means that the point of interest, you have to understand it from where he got that interest, how you want to switch to that part, it becomes much more genuine.
Paul: So, yes, a project with proper storytelling is important, if you have not worked, really, in an organization, because then you won't understand what are the production issues, if anything, he might ask you, like, with respect to volume update, a simple question.
Paul: Okay, you will get stuck. Okay? Because, just because you have not worked, so few things are there. Okay, that story point, storytelling, so at least a POC.
loki: Yeah.
Paul: that you need to work on. Then, it becomes much more genuine.
loki: Oh, good point, yeah.
loki: Thanks, Bob.
Paul: All right. Guys, so tomorrow's session, the two chunkers we will complete, and then we will start with hybrid search. So, important topics are going to be covered, like, hybrid search.
Paul: IUD, BM25, okay, arrays and King, all these concepts will come. Okay? So, just be sure that the next few classes are important. Okay, so don't miss these classes for everyone. Okay, so bye everyone, thanks for joining, let's meet tomorrow.